<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Physicke, to cure the most dangerous disease of desperation Collected for the direction and comfort of such Christians as trauayling and being heauie loaden in their consciences, with the burthen of their sinnes, stand in danger either in time of their sicknesse to fall away from their God, through deepe despaire, or else in time of their health, to yeelde to one desparate end, or other, to the ruine and vtter confusion of both bodyes and soules for euer. By W.W.</title>
            <author>Willymat, William, d. 1615.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25762</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102526</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838303</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838303</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2677</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15495)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2677)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1088:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Physicke, to cure the most dangerous disease of desperation Collected for the direction and comfort of such Christians as trauayling and being heauie loaden in their consciences, with the burthen of their sinnes, stand in danger either in time of their sicknesse to fall away from their God, through deepe despaire, or else in time of their health, to yeelde to one desparate end, or other, to the ruine and vtter confusion of both bodyes and soules for euer. By W.W.</title>
                  <author>Willymat, William, d. 1615.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. White] for Robert Boulton, and are to be sold at his shop in Chauneerie lane neere Holborne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: William Willimat.</note>
                  <note>A variant, with imprint: "Printed [by W. White] for Robert Boulton, and ar eto be sold at his shop in Chauncerie lane neere Holborne. 1605". From 25761.5, published in 1604.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Despair --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2677:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2677:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PHYSICKE, TO CVRE THE MOST dangerous Diſeaſe of <hi>Deſperation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Collected for the direction and comfort of ſuch Chriſtians as trauayling and being heauie loaden in their Conſciences, with the burthen of their ſinnes, ſtand in danger either in time of their ſickneſſe to fall away from their God, through deepe Deſpaire, or elſe in time of their health, to yeelde to one deſperate end, or other, to the ruine and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confuſion of both bodyes and ſoules for euer.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 18.14.</bibl> Who can beare a wounded ſpirite?</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Aug. in lib, de vtilitate paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae agendae.</bibl> 
               <hi>Ne deſperatione auge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> peccata pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitus eſt penitentiae p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſus n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſperando au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>amus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis incer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed for <hi>Robert Boulton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Chauncerie lane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Holborne. 1605.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2677:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2677:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Honorable, the Lord <hi>THOMAS HOWARD,</hi> Earle of Suffolke, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of Walden, Knight of the moſt honorable order of the Garter, <hi>Lord High Chamberlaine to the</hi> Kinges moſt excellent Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and one of his moſt honorable priuie Counſaile.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat, manifolde, and</hi> terrible (Right Honorable) are the tumults, turmoyles, troubles, feares, and angui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, which the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of ſinnes bypaſt, and preſent, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned with the carefull contemplation, and inward conſideration of Gods gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous threatninges, and wrathfull indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſet foorth in holy Scriptures, bring vnto weake, troubled, and ignorant, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. Great againe is the diligence,
<pb facs="tcp:2677:3"/> and continuall is the wandering to and fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Sathan, that deadly and mortall foe of mankind, to tempt and aſsault, to bring to deſperation, &amp; deuoure ſinners at all times, &amp; in all places; but eſpecially in the dayes of affliction, troubles, plagues, peſtilences, and ſickneſses; yea, and moſt of all at the hower of death, when man is at the weakeſt, and moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and vnable to withſtand him; when mans memorie fayleth him, and his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces waxe dull, his body is tormented and feebled, his heart faynteth, his wittes decay, and euery part of his body ceaſſeth to performe and fulfill his due office: then, euen then I ſay, moſt vigilant, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, and buſie is that foule feende to vexe, trouble, diſquiet, to turmoyle men, and to worke blaſphemie and deſperation in their heartes by laying before the eyes of their conſciences al their former ſinfull maner of lyuing, and vngodly conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the breach of Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and his greeuous wrath against offenders; the vnſupportable paynes, and
<pb facs="tcp:2677:3"/> torturing tormentes, death, and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which, are prepared for the wicked with the Diuell and his damned Angels. The conſideration of theſe thinges, and the great negligence, careleſneſſe, and contempt of prouiding remedies and phiſicke in due time, againſt this dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous diſeaſe of Deſperation, hath moued mee at this preſent, to employ my Penne, according to that one poore talent which the Lord God hath committed vnto mee to the ſetting foorth of this Treatiſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, therby to arme and furniſh poore ignorant Chriſtians with ſome neceſſarie counſaile, comfort, and ſpirituall phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, whereby they may become the more able and readie in time of neede, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende themſelues; yea, and to propell and driue backe their common enemie: the Diuell tempting and entiſing to the moſt deadly ſinne of Deſperation.</p>
            <p>Theſe my poore laboures (written both for the comfort of my ſelfe, and ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of mine owne Fayth, and for the like good of others, if they will for their
<pb facs="tcp:2677:4"/> owne good, take the paines to reade, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and accept thereof) I your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours poore incumbent of the medietie of the Rectorie of <hi>Ruskington</hi> in <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colnſhire,</hi> the true and vndoubted Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage whereof lately was the Kinges Maieſties, and now is yours to diſpoſe at your Honours good lyking, haue attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſend forth to the view of the world vnder your ſhielding protection, and patrocinie. And ſo with my humble pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition for th' acceptance hereof, with that ſubmisſion that beſt befitteth my ſelfe, and belongeth to a perſon of ſo great place, &amp; calling, I humbly lake my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At <hi>Ruskington</hi> in <hi>Lincoln<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi>
                  <date>this firſt of Nouember. <hi>1604.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Hon. euer readie to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded in all Chriſtian dutie, <hi>William Willimat.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:2677:4"/>
            <head>A PREFACE TO THE Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a wonder of the world, a wonder to be ſeriouſly marked, and diligentlye conſidered of; and a wonder being ſeriouſly marked, &amp; diligently conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of, worthy to be deeply waighed, and inwardly to be layde vp in mens heartes as a thing moſt neceſſarie, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and auaileable to Chriſtian pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie, and euerlaſting felicitie both of ſoule and body,<note place="margin">The firſt thing to be wondred a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſeriouſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dered of.</note> to ſee and to thinke of it, how carefull, watchfull, diligent, earneſt, and painefull, almoſt all the world euery where is to auoyde, to preuent, to cure, and to remedie, all ſuch troubles, croſſes, griefes, mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, infirmities, and ſickneſſes, as do or may befall the body: And on the other
<pb facs="tcp:2677:5"/> ſide to ſee, or finde ſo few watchfull, carefull, and painefull to auoyde, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, cure, or expell the moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous wounds of the ſpirit, the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the conſcience, or Deſperation; a miſchiefe of al other miſchiefes, moſt needfull to be looked vnto.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſecond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onored at, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeriouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dered of.</note>It is a wonder to ſee, and conſider, how many there are in the world which either loath and are afraide of bodily ſickneſſe, or loue &amp; likes health, will ſend for and ſeeke, runne and ride after bodily Phyſitions, and enquire after the beſt, the moſt expert &amp; moſt skilfull of them, to learne by their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and to be aduiſed by their counſaile (though it coſt their purſſe full deare) how to purge and auoyde ſuch corrupt humours as may breed (though not preſently bring foorth) noyſome diſeaſes, and ſickneſſes: how carefull and how ſcrupulous they are to keepe a temperate order and a dyet in eating and drinking: and how mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate they will be in ſleepe, and all
<pb facs="tcp:2677:5"/> other bodyly exerciſes: And on the other ſide, how few there be in the world that will either abate their ſleepe, for-goe their pleaſures, abridge their dyets, or ſeeke after the ſpirituall Phyſition or prepare phyſick to purge and expell thoſe dangerous &amp; peccant humors, of notorious and hainous ſinnes, which in time will both breed and bring foorth the moſt deadly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of Deſperation, the very Peſte of ſoule and body for euer.</p>
            <p>It is a wonder to ſee,<note place="margin">The third thing to be wondred at.</note> how many abhor, and are afraide of worldly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, and for the auoyding thereof, and for the loue and liking of tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie riches, will with great carke and care riſe vp early, and late take their reſt: they will fare hardly, and go clad full barely: they will hazard both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes and ſoules; they will toyle and teare their fleſh in vnmeaſurable la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures by land and ſea, be the weather faire, be it foule, <hi>per mare pauperiem fugientes, per ſaxa, perignes:</hi> And yet
<pb facs="tcp:2677:6"/> on the other ſide, how few can abide any coſtes, charges, or paines, to eſcape and remedie ſpirituall decayes: to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde pouertie of conſcience, or in time before it be too late, to beware that they be not plunged ere they be aware into the moſt deadly and diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh gulph of Deſperation; as though ſaluation, and peace of a godly conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, were a matter not worthy the talking of, or labouring for.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A thing to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>It is a lamentable thing to behold, how many in the world will vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take and attempt any thing, be it neuer ſo chargeable and troubleſome, not ſluggiſh not ſleepie; not careleſſe and ſlouthfull, but moſt earneſt &amp; watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, moſt carefull &amp; painefull, at euery aſſay; by prudence and proweſſe, by witte and by warineſſe, by counſaile and by cunning, by learning and by labouring; ambitiouſly to hunt, gaine, and gape after honour, and vnfatigab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſeeke to attaine fame, and highly account of it to be gazed on, and talked
<pb facs="tcp:2677:6"/> of, with the eyes &amp; tongues of all men: And againe, how few take any cate at all, or once endeuour themſelues to auoyde ſhame, and confuſion in the preſence of the Almightie, to become glorious in the ſight of God and his Angels, and to vſe and exerciſe any of thoſe good meanes and inſtrumentes ordeyned and appoynted of God for the increaſe of Fayth, Hope, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; and for the weakning and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning of all deſperation &amp; diffidence in Gods infinite mercies, and infallible promiſes.</p>
            <p>It is a lamentable thing to marke and conſider how vigilant, carefull,<note place="margin">The ſecond thing to be lamented.</note> &amp; heedfull many of the wyſer, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpecter ſort of men of this world will be to eſcape, and auoyde, all the penalties, paynes, and puniſhmentes, prouided and ſet downe, for offenders of mortall mens lawes; how painefull they will be in Penall Statutes, &amp; how skilfull in euery braunch of the Ciuill Lawes, leaſt they ſhould ignorantly
<pb facs="tcp:2677:7"/> incurre the dangers of impriſonment, of loſſe of landes, forfeytures of their goodes, or death it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Many haue greater ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of mortall mens lawes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen of Gods lawes.</note>But the mightie God, the only high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Law-giuer, that Lord of Lordes, and King of all Kinges; Let him or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne, publiſh, and proclayme his Lawes, Statutes, and Ordinaunces, to be harkened vnto, obſerued, and kept, and that vnder neuer ſo rigorous and ſeueere conditions, puniſhmentes, and penalties, How few men will ſearch his Booke of Statutes and Lawes? How few are afrayde of his not tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porarie, but euerlaſting threatninges and puniſhmentes, contayned in his Lawes? and how few men regarde, eſteeme, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thankfully embrace his couenant of Reconciliation, ſet foorth in his moſt ioyfull, and comfortable Goſpell?</p>
            <p>And yet moſt certaine it is, that all theſe aforeſayd thinges, ſo much to be wondred at, and ſo greatly to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented for; ſo lightly looked on, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:2677:7"/> ſmally regarded, and ſo little thought on, &amp; many ſuch other of the like fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie &amp; order of diſorders, &amp; ſinnes, being delighted in, and ſecurely conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in, without all care or indeuour to forſake them in time, by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and true returning to the Lord, do firſt breed and ingender, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes bring foorth Deſperation; then the which, all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uries, and Diuels in hell, can not lightly excogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate nor finde out a greater torment, or a more intollerable paine, and that becauſe that all other tormentes, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, and paines, are but temporall, and purſue men no further then bodily death: but this endeth not with bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily death, but becommeth eternall. Whoſoeuer then he be, that is once ſurely catcht in this nette of Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hee needes no moe accuſers to come againſt him, then his former vnrepented ſinnes, which lye at the doore to arreſt him; his owne heart will giue euidence againſt him, and
<pb facs="tcp:2677:8"/> his owne iniquitie will plead him to be guiltie, and that to his owne face.</p>
            <p>Vpon conſideration of theſe things, I haue now in this Treatiſe following, (good Chriſtian Reader) endeuoured my ſelfe to ſet downe, Firſt, a defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Deſperation;</hi> then the gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſneſſe thereof: after this, certaine principall cauſes thereof; togeather with remedies for the ſame: and laſtly, a generall Preſeruatiue againſt <hi>Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> aryſing of what cauſe ſo euer: To the intent, that the children of God, falling by ſome occaſions into ſome degrees of it, (for if it rage in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, in the opinion of ſome lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Writers, it is an euill incurable, and vnrecouerable) may with the more eaſe and quietneſſe be recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſaued as it were out of the Diuels clawes; euen out of as great danger as euer was the poore Sheepe that <hi>Dauid</hi> tooke out of the Beares or Lions mouth.<note place="margin">1. Sam 17.34 35.</note>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2677:8"/>
            <p>Accept hereof (gentle Reader) with no worſe a minde, then I haue attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be the writer; and then I doubt not, but it ſhall either miniſter vnto thine heart ſome comfortable Phiſicke, or els giue thee occaſion to ſeeke, reade, or collect a better.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in all chriſtian affection,</hi> W. W.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2677:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:2677:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2677:10"/>
            <head>The Contents of this Booke, entreated of in euery ſeuerall <hi>Page as followeth.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>A Definition of euery thing which is to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, or reaſoned of, is neceſſarie, and wherefore. Page. 1.</item>
               <item>The Definition of Deſperation of two ſorts. Page. 1. &amp; 2.</item>
               <item>Two kindes of Deſperation: the one wicked, the other good and holy. Page. 3.</item>
               <item>Three thinges eſpecially to be noted in the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Deſperation. Page. 4.</item>
               <item>God is conſtant and faythfull: and how, and wherein. Page. 4.</item>
               <item>The duetie of the faythfull towardes God, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Gods faythfulnes towardes him. Page. 5.</item>
               <item>The horriblnes of the ſinne of Diffidence, Miſtruſt, or Deſperation. Page. 5.</item>
               <item>When eſpecially the Diuell deginneth to tempt to Deſperation. Page. 6.</item>
               <item>What kind of Phiſicke and ſurgerie the Diuell practiſeth. Page. 7.</item>
               <item>The abſurd dealings of ſuch as yeeld to deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Page. 8.</item>
               <item>What great inconueniences they fall into, that yeeld to Deſperation. Page. 8.</item>
               <item>Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> his opinion concerning the hainouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſinne of Deſperation. Page. 9.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Charybdis</hi> not ſo dangerous as Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration. Page. 9.</item>
               <item>The dangers of Deſperation. Page. 10. &amp; 11.</item>
               <item>Of the degrees by which the Diuell draweth men into Deſperation. Page. 13.</item>
               <item>The Diuel the chiefe cauſe of Deſperation. Page. 13.</item>
               <item>The forerunners of Deſperation. Page. 14.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:2677:10"/>
               <item>What the Diuel wil obict to bring vs to deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Page. 15.</item>
               <item>Ignoraunce the ſecond cauſe of Deſperation Page. 16.</item>
               <item>Ignoraunce the mother of Deſperation. Page. 17.</item>
               <item>Seruitude or bondage of ſinne, the third cauſe of Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Page. 17.</item>
               <item>The wofull effectes of ſinne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Page. 18.</item>
               <item>The fourth cauſe of Deſperation. Page. 18.</item>
               <item>The manifold aduerſaries of mans ſaluation: all which the Diuell vſeth as meanes to Deſperation, Page. 19.</item>
               <item>The fift cauſe of Deſperation. Page. 20. &amp; 21.</item>
               <item>The ſixt cauſe of Deſperation. Page. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</item>
               <item>Long cuſtome groweth into a ſecond nature. Page. 22.</item>
               <item>The firſt preſeruatiue againſt Desperation. Page. 88.</item>
               <item>An example ſhewing that many men put more truſt in mortall men then in God. Page. 89.</item>
               <item>An other profe, that many put more truſt in mortall man then in God. Page. 90.</item>
               <item>The ſecond generall helpe againſt Deſperation. Page. 91.</item>
               <item>The third generall helpe againſt Deſperation. Page. 92.</item>
               <item>What ſoeuer could be looked for at Gods handes, or what ſoeuer man could be charged with, that hath Chriſt performed. Page. 93.</item>
               <item>The fourth generall helpe for the auoyding of Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Page. 94.</item>
               <item>The fift generall helpe againſt Deſperation. Page. 95.</item>
               <item>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Iames</hi> their counſaile againſt the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and aſſaultes of Sathan. Page. 24.</item>
               <item>A deſcription of the armour with which S. <hi>Paul</hi> would haue Chriſtians to reſiſt the Diuell Page. 25.</item>
               <item>The firſt kind of Armour to reſiſt the Diuell with. Page. 25.</item>
               <item>The ſecond kind of Armour wherewith the Diuell is to be reſiſted. Page. 25.</item>
               <item>Whereby the Diuel is imboldned to tempt, &amp; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:2677:11"/> on the other ſide he is diſcouraged. Page. 26.</item>
               <item>The third kind of Armour againſt Sathan. Page. 27.</item>
               <item>The fourth Armour againſt Sathan. Page. 28.</item>
               <item>What Fayth is. Page. 29.</item>
               <item>The fift kind of Armour to reſiſt the Diuell. Page. 29.</item>
               <item>Chriſt himſelfe an example how to reſiſt the diuel. Page. 30.</item>
               <item>The Scriptures do miniſter ſtore of Armoure againſt euery kind of temptation. Page. 31.</item>
               <item>The ſixt kind of Chriſtian Armour. Page. 32.</item>
               <item>Remedies againſt Ignoraunce. Page. 34.</item>
               <item>The dangers of willfull Ignoraunce. Page. 35.</item>
               <item>What the Ignorant muſt do. Page. 35.</item>
               <item>Counſayle very neceſſary for the Ignoraunt. Page. 36.</item>
               <item>What the Miniſters of Gods word are. Page. 36.</item>
               <item>How the Miniſters of Gods word are to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of. Page. 37.</item>
               <item>Of the great ſeruitude and bondage of ſinnes, and of the remedies thereof. Page. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Examples tending to the ſtrengthening of our Fayth, Hope, and Patience againſt, Deſperation. Page. 39. &amp; 40.</item>
               <item>Wherefore Chriſt came into this world. Page. 41. 42. &amp; 43.</item>
               <item>What maner of righteouſnes God requireth at our handes. Page. 45.</item>
               <item>Sinne dwelleth euen in the beleeuers, and in the moſt righteous in the world; but yet raigneth not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it condemne them, and why. Page. 46. &amp; 47.</item>
               <item>Places of Scripture ſetting foorth Gods great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Page. 49.</item>
               <item>A Catalogue or rehearſall of many thinges whereby the Diuell craftely tempteth many men to ſinne and Deſperation. Page. 50.</item>
               <item>How the Diuell tempteth by riches. Page. 50.</item>
               <item>How the Diuell tempteth by pouertie. Page. 51.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:2677:11"/>
               <item>How the Diuell tempteth by friendes. Page. 51.</item>
               <item>How the Diuell tempteth by enemies, Page. 52.</item>
               <item>How the Diuell tempteth by carefulneſſe. Page. 52.</item>
               <item>How the Diuell tempteth by ſecuritie and careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Page. 52.</item>
               <item>How the Diuell tempteth by ſtrength, by health, ableneſſe of body, beautie; by honor &amp; dignie, by quickneſſe of ſpirit, &amp; ſharpneſſe of wit. Page. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; 53.</item>
               <item>How the Diuell tempteth by Gods word, and how he will abuſe, wreſt, &amp; misapply Gods word. Page. 53. &amp; 54.</item>
               <item>The true vſe of thoſe Scriptures which the Diuell ſeeketh to abuſe, to bring men to Deſperation thereby. Page. 55.</item>
               <item>The comfort and commodities of the croſſes and afflictions of Gods children. Page. 57. &amp; 58.</item>
               <item>Why God ſendeth euilles to his children, and how he ſendeth comforts in the middeſt of euils. Page. 59.</item>
               <item>How God loueth, and dealeth with his children. Page. 60.</item>
               <item>Gods roddes of what ſort they are. Page. 61.</item>
               <item>What God ſeeketh to worke by dealing hardly with his children. Page. 62.</item>
               <item>Gods affection to his children like vnto a kind louing mothers affection. Page. 63. &amp; 64.</item>
               <item>God dealeth with his children as Phiſitions and Surgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do with their Patientes. Page. 66.</item>
               <item>God vſeth ſometimes the ſeruice and miniſterie of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels and of wicked men. Page. 67.</item>
               <item>The wicked are not be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered by their troubles and afflictions. Page. 67.</item>
               <item>Whence it commeth that afflictions and croſſes profit Gods children. Page. 67.</item>
               <item>The conceites and opinions of the wicked in their aduerſities and troubles. Page. 68. &amp; 69.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:2677:12"/>
               <item>The endes that the Diuell bringes the wicked vnto by their afflictions, troubles and croſſes. Page. 70.</item>
               <item>Two commodities to be reaped by the lyues, and manner of the deathes of the wicked. Page. 71.</item>
               <item>The great danger of cuſtome of ſinne, and of delaying of amendement of life. Page. 71. &amp; 72.</item>
               <item>A compariſon ſhewing the danger of long cuſtome and weltering in ſinne. Page. 72. &amp; 73.</item>
               <item>Whence repentance &amp; amendement of life are to be had, and how they are to be come by. Page. 74,</item>
               <item>Many are and may be deceyued in the manner and time of their repentaunce. Page. 75.</item>
               <item>A note for ſuch as deferre repentance vnto their laſt day. Page. 75.</item>
               <item>Examples ſhewing that it is dangerous truſting vnto the laſt hower. Page. 76.</item>
               <item>Notable examples of ſodaine and vnprouided death, out of holy Scriptures &amp; other writers. Page. 76. 77. 78 79.</item>
               <item>A catalogue or rehearſall of ſundry lets and impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes which oftentimes fall out when we come to our laſt hower, to hinder and put by that late re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, which ſo many truſt to at the end of their liues. Page. 81. &amp; 82.</item>
               <item>The effectes of choler in time of extreame ſicknes. Page. 82.</item>
               <item>The maner how the Diuell will buſie himſelfe to hinder repentance at our laſt pant. Page. 83.</item>
               <item>The example of Ioſeph of Arimathea moſt worthy to be imitated. Page. 85.</item>
               <item>The vſe and cuſtome of the <hi>Egiptians</hi> to bridle euill actions. Page. 86.</item>
               <item>The notable and imitable example of King <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias.</hi> Page. 86.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2677:12"/>
            <head>Of Deſperation.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The firſt Chapter conteyning the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Diuiſion of Deſperation.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>. <hi>T. Cicero,</hi> that moſt worthy Father of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> eloquence, was of that minde,<note place="margin">A definition o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> euery thing which is to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted or reaſoned of, is neceſſary, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note> that euery thing which was to be reaſoned &amp; diſputed of, ſhould firſt begin at the Definition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that ſo it might briefly be vnderſtoode what the ſubſtaunce of the matter was, whereof reaſoning or diſputation was to be holden: Of the like opinion &amp; minde am I at this preſent, concerning the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous peſte of moſt wicked and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Deſperation; being the matter which now I haue in hand (through Gods aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance) to write of.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2677:13"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Definition of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is of two ſortes.</note>The Definition then of Deſperation, I finde and read to be of two ſortes as concerning the wordes, and yet in ſence, and ſubſtance of matter little differing one from the other:<note place="margin">The firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of Deſperation</note> Whereof the one is, <hi>Deſperatio eſt horribilis mertis &amp; c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rdis ſeu conſcientiae trepidatio ex ſenſu irae diuinae prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter peccatum concepta cum metu aeternae dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacionis ſine vlla expectatione veniae:</hi> Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is an horrible feare, or trembling of the minde &amp; heart or conſcience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued through a ſenſe and feeling of Gods wrath for ſinne; with a feare of eternall damnation, without all expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or hope of pardon or forgiueneſſe thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond Definition of Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>The other (which is a farre more aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Definition) is this, <hi>Deſperatio est malum quo quis diffidit de voluntate dei, aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans malitiam ſuam magnitudinem diuinae miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ricordiae &amp; bonitatis excedere:</hi> Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is an euill through which a man miſtruſteth diſpaireth vtterly, and is paſt all hope of the good will of God, verily thinking that his naughtineſſe, or ſinnes, excell the mercies and goodnes of God; according to that ſaying of the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperat man <hi>Cain;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Mine iniquitie is greater
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2677:13"/> then can be pardoned. Geneſ. 4.13.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus it being made plaine and eaſie what Deſperation is, by theſe aforeſayd Definitions, it followeth in the next place, (to proceede after the ſame order that the ſayd <hi>Cicero</hi> vſed) that I ſpeake of diuiſion of Deſperation; which I likewiſe find and reade to be of two kindes:<note place="margin">Two kindes of Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion: the one wicked, the other holy.</note> the one a wicked kind of Deſperation of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, power, goodnes, &amp; mercie towards ſinners, the matter which heere I am to entreate of: The other an holy Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of a mans owne power in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of eternall life, conceyued and wrought by a ſenſe or feeling of a mans owne defectes, infirmities, and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Concerning this former kind of Deſperation, being eſpecially the marke which I would haue poore ſilly diſtreſſed ſoules to haue a diligent and a watchfull eye vnto, to the intent that both my ſelfe, and my poore brethren, lyuing and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring yet with mee in the militant Church of Chriſt heere on earth, may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forewarned (for that as the ſay <hi>Tela praeuiſa minus nocent</hi>) of this moſt ſubtill and deadly ſtrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>geme, concerning this moſt dongerous and fatall aſſaulting en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2677:14"/> of the arch-enemie of our ſoules, this deepe Deſpaire, and diuelliſh ſoule-poyſon, I haue thought good by the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this ſhort Treatiſe, to put my ſelfe and others in remembrance of theſe three poyntes;<note place="margin">Three things eſpecially to be noted in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</note> to wit, firſt of the haynouſnhſſe, greeuouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe, &amp; perniciouſneſſe of Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration. Secondly, of the cauſes thereof: and thirdly of the remedies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The ſecond Chapter, wherein is deſcribed how haynous greeuous, hurtfull, and pernitious, the ſinne of Deſperation is.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN ſundry and manifold places of holy Scriptures are we taught,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.9. 2. Theſ. 3.3. 1 Iohn. 1.9.</note> that <hi>God is faythfull:</hi> faythfull in his wordes, and true in all his promiſes: <hi>All the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God are Yea and Amen:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor 1.20. God is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, and how, or wherein. Reuel 15.3. 2. Cor. 6.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Faythfull in his mercies, for they neuer fayle: Fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, iuſt &amp; true, are his wayes; according to the Song of the holy Angels, <hi>Reue. 1.5.3.</hi> Yea moreouer, God is carefull for the Faythfull, and hath promiſed to be <hi>their God, and they ſhall be his people.</hi> It is thy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2677:14"/> duetie therefore, ô man! to doe God this honour, to beleeue without all wauering, doubting, or deſpayring; that God hath both Power and Will to do all thinges that he promiſeth,<note place="margin">The duetie of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full towards God in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of gods faythfulnes towardes him.</note> and not to permit any ſuch cogitations, thought, or conceite, once to enter into thine heart, as that God ſhould prooue himſelfe a lyar; or that it ſhall not come to paſſe, which he hath promiſed. But if thou once ſuffer the diſtruſt and diffidence in Gods promiſed mercies (through the multitude of thy ſinnes, and the greeuouſneſſe of thine offences, through the nature of ſinne it ſelfe and the craftie ingeſtion and ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of Satan) to take hold of, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe thine heart: O horrible &amp; greeuous is this laſt ſinne of Deſpayring, which thou addeſt to thy former ſinnes.<note place="margin">The horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes of the ſinne of diffidence, miſtruſt, or deſperation.</note> So hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, ſo hurtfull and pernitious, is this thy ſinne of Diffidence and Diſtruſt in Gods mercies to be obtayned, according to his promiſed Word, that I may ſay of thee, as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſayd of <hi>Iudas</hi> the traytor,<note place="margin">Aug. in Lib. de vtiliti to paenitentia agendae.</note> 
                  <hi>Non tam ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lus quod comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſisti, quam indulgentiae deſperatio facit te penitus interi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e:</hi> Not ſo much the ſinne which thou haſt done, as thy deſpai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of forgiuenes, hath vtterly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2677:15"/> caſt thee away. Surely <hi>Iudas</hi> his deſpaire and diſtruſt (according to <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> his opinion) was a more greeuous ſinne, then his treaſon in the betraying of his Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Whereunto agreeth <hi>S. Iero. Magis inquit offendit deum Iudas in hoc quod deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando ſeipſum ſuſpendit, quam in hoc quod deum tradidit. Deſperatio enim reddit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem maledictum, &amp; protectione dei indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. ſuper Pſal. 108.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudas</hi> (ſayth <hi>S. Ierome</hi>) more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended God herein, that in deſpaire he hanged himſelfe, then in that he betraied his Lord and Maiſter: For Deſperation maketh a man accurſed, and vnworthy Gods protection. And thus likewiſe <hi>Cain</hi> his deſpayring in Gods mercie after his murther committed, was a more greeuous ſinne, then the ſhedding of his brother <hi>Abel</hi> his blood: For to adde Deſpayre to former ſinnes, is to draw ſinne after ſinne as it were with Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roopes, to heape ſinne vpon ſinne, to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the meaſure of iniquitie, and ſo to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe ſwift and moſt certaine damnation. It is in deede the faſhion and olde wont of Sathan,<note place="margin">When eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Diuell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to tempt to deſpaire.</note> to perſwade man (when he hath once committed many haynous ſinnes) after his other ſinnes, to Diſpaire,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2677:15"/> and ſo to commit the greater ſinne after the leſſer: which is as much as if an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned ignorant and a murthering Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſhould cauſe his Patient for the remedying of a litle cold taken, to drinke the iuice of Hemlocke, which by adding cold to cold, is moſt ſure to bring preſent death: Or as if a man hauing an Ach in one of his fingers, ſhould cut off the whole hand to take away the Ach of a finger. Euen ſuch like Phiſicke and Surgery doth the Diuell practiſe to miniſter vnto lewde and wilfull ſinners,<note place="margin">Note what kind of phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke &amp; ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie the Diuell practiſeth.</note> when he enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth and draweth them after many prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent haynous ſinnes, through deſpaire of finding mercie &amp; forgiuenes to ſhorten their liues, by killing and murthering themſelues, by poyſoning, by ſtabbing, by throat-cutting, by drowning, by <hi>Iudas</hi>-like hanging of themſelues; and finally by caſting off all vſe of Fayth, all vſe of Hope, and ſo quite to deſpaire of Gods mercie: then the which, what can be a more dangerous courſe for any man to yeelde vnto? What can be more fooliſh or contrary to all reaſon, if a mans reaſon were not blinded and bewitched that he could not ſee nor perceiue, nor conſider
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2677:16"/> well of it, then whiles a man is afraide of water, preſently to caſt himſelfe heade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into it, and ſo ſeeingly and wittingly to drowne himſelfe?<note place="margin">The ol ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alinges of ſuch as ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yeeld to deſperation.</note> or then whiles a man is afraid of fire, preſently to runne into it and to diſpatch himſelfe therin? Or whiles a man is afraid of hell fire, out of hand moſt deſperately to plunge himſelfe into the daungers thereof?</p>
               <p>And yet ſuch as theſe are the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and temptations of the Diuell, to a man whole barking conſcience conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually pangeth and plagueth him for his ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Such as theſe are the fruites of the moſt monſtrous ſinne of Deſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aring of Gods mercy and grace.</p>
               <p>May not he be accounted worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mad, that is to forwarde and ready to yeeld vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,<note place="margin">Marke this o man, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt thou yeelde to deſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before thou be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t great incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap>ces thou y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and to follow after the Diuels whiſtle, alluring &amp; entiſing vnto deſperation, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is no meanes to diminiſh, but to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe ſinne, and the rewardes of ſinne; ſeeing that it is no reliefe, but an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting burthen and griefe of the ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeeing that it is not a deliuerie of the ſoule, but a certaine deſtruction of the ſoule: ſeeing it is not a redemption, but an vndoubted
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2677:16"/> condemnation of ſoule and body for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
               <p>And finally, ſeeing that it chaungeth temporall griefe into eternall griefe, and the panges of conſcience into the paines of hell for euer. And thus is verified that ſaying of Saint <hi>Bernard, Deſperatio auget peccatum, Deſperatio maior eſt omnibus pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catis, Deſperatio peior eſt omni peccato:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erbards opinion concerning the hainouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the ſinne of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</note> Deſperation encreaſeth ſinne: Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is greater then all other ſinnes, Deſperation is worſe then all other ſinnes.</p>
               <p>This is a thouſand times worſe then the daungerous rocke Scilla, againſt which ſo many poore Mariners haue da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed their Shippes,<note place="margin">Scilla and Charybdis not ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous as deſperation.</note> to the great loſſe both of Shippes, goodes, and liues: or then that no leſſe daungerous gulfe Charybdis, which hath deuowred vp ſo many paſſengers: For at this vnfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate and deadly rocke of Deſperation, many thouſandes of poore ſoules, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with the burthen of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities, and turmoyled in their conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciences with the waues of fearefull thoughtes, and troubleſome conceites by the bluſtring blaſtes and ſurgy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2677:17"/> ſtormes of Gods vengeance threatned againſt ſinners, both haue and dayly doe make dangerous &amp; fearefull ſhipwracke. This is a worſe dungion for both ſoules and bodyes of poore deſperate ſinners, then was the Denne of Lions into the which the Rulers, Officers, and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of King <hi>Darius</hi> cauſed <hi>Daniel</hi> to be caſt,<note place="margin">Dan. 6.17.</note> and cloſed vp: Yea, and this is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen times worſe then the ſeuentimes hoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted burning Ouen or Fornace,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.19.</note> into the which that proud Idolatrous King <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> commaunded <hi>Sidrach, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h,</hi> and <hi>Abean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>go,</hi> the true Seruantes and worſhippers of the onely true and euerliuing God, to be caſt in. This is that incurable remedileſſe, and deſperate ſore wounde and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ladie, which the Prophets of God <hi>Ieremie</hi> and <hi>Micheas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 3. Mich. 1.</note> in their dayes complayned of among their people. This is that great ſtoppe and let that hindereth and reſiſteth Gods holy Grace from flowing and entring into die ſoules of ſinfull men. This is the Axe that heaweth and choppeth a ſunder the Chaynes wherewith God in his great mercie and mercifull kindneſſe, would draw the heartes of ſinners vnto himſelfe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2677:17"/> by Repentance;<note place="margin">Ozeas. 11.</note> whereof ſpeaketh the Prophet <hi>Ozeas. Truſt in the Lord, and do good,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 37.3.</note> ſayth the holy Gloſt by the Prophet <hi>Dauid:</hi> where he placeth &amp; ſetteth <hi>truſt in God</hi> in the firſt place, and <hi>doing good</hi> in the ſecond: <hi>truſting in God,</hi> goeth before as the Miſtris, and <hi>doing good,</hi> followeth and attendeth on as the Hand-mayde. For as it is ſayd, <hi>Spes alit agricolas,</hi> were it not for Hope, the Husband mans heart would burſt; Hope nowriſheth his heart: Euen ſo Diſpaire and Diffidence, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt in God, is a Stepmother to well doing, and draweth backe from doing good; according to the ſaying of a learned Writer vpon the ſayd 37. Pſalme,<note place="margin">Muſculus in Pſalm. 37.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio &amp; diffidentia abſtrahit ab omni ſtudio boni, nam cogitat omnia fieri frustra: ita nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ex ſpe &amp; fiducia promanant mortaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conatus, vt ex ipſis cenatibus ſatis liqueat quid quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſperat:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deſperation draweth men backe from all wel doing, and why.</note> Deſperation and Miſtruſt draweth backe from all deſire of well doing, for it thinketh all to be but loſt labour: for ſo doe all mens labours and endeuours flow and ſpring from Hope and Truſt, that euery mans doinges doe plainely teſtifie what he hopeth or truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:2677:18"/>
               <p>And now let this ſuffize briefly to giue a taſte how great and greeuous hurtfull and pernicious this ſinne of Deſperation is.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The third Chapter conteyning the chiefeſt and moſt principall cauſes of Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THat memorable and notable ſaying of <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> in one of his Homilies, mooueth mee to thinke, and heere to commit it to writing, that one cauſe of Deſperation, and not the leaſt, but rather the primarie and principall cauſe of all other, aryſeth from the ſubtile, cunning, and coſoning counſaile, inducement, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, and allurement of the Diuell: for ſayth <hi>S. Grigorie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. in qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m in graui peccato miſer homo libitur: ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> idet ei diabolus ne poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iteat, ne confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>atur, peccatum leue et mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum in cord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> affirmat: miſericordiam prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat, lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gum ſpacium vitae promittit, perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere in peccato ſuggerit, vt ſic in contemtum dei, &amp; deſperationem ſui inducat &amp; pereat:</hi> When wretched man ſlippeth into ſome greeuous ſinne, the Diuels counſaile
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2677:18"/> is, that he repent not at all for it, that he confeſſe it not: hee tels him in his heart,<note place="margin">The degrees by which the Diuell draweth men on into deſperation.</note> that it is but a light and ſmall offence: hee ſayes, God is full of mercie, he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him long life, he ſuggeſteth vnto him to lie ſtill in ſinne, that by theſe meanes he may bring him at the laſt into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God, and into vtter Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo he may become a caſt-away for euer. Heere doth <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> in moſt manifeſt and plaine wordes deſcribe, and decipher the Diuell himſelfe to be the author, and ſo conſequently the chiefeſt cauſer, and cauſe, of this horrible ſoule murthering Diſperation; and heere alſo doth he ſet downe by what ſteps and degrees hee bringes and leades a poore careleſſe wretched man into Deſpaire.</p>
               <p>Now conſider this moreouer, that if <hi>Sathan</hi> that archenemie of mans wel-fare,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> durſt very boldly and ſawcely without any bidding, preſume to thruſt himſelfe into Gods preſence amongſt his holy Angells; if he durſt ſo ſubtelly and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly, diſſemblingly and lyingly, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle and aſſault our fyrſte Parentes <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> beeing yet innocentes,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> vnſtayned, and pure from all ſinne:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2677:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> Nay more then al this, if he durſt approch, and with diuers temptations aſſault and allure <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> himſelfe,<note place="margin">Math. 4.3.</note> both God and Man; and yet Man free from any ſpot or blemiſh of ſinne, endeuoring himſelfe to the vttermoſt of his skill and power, if it had been paſsible, to haue brought him, and wrought him to his owne wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked will. Alas, is it any maruaile then if he doe as diligently and buſily beſtirre himſelfe with his manifolde wyles, and guyles, to aſſayle vs weake, poore, and miſerable ſinners? Who (without the dayly and howerly ſtrenghthening of Gods holy ſpirit) are of ourſelues prompt, apt, and ready, euery hower to decline and fall away from God,<note place="margin">The fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners of deſperation, except wee looke to our ſelues in time.</note> and to fall vnto Idolatrie, blaſphemie, periurie, murther, whoredome, theft, pride, diſobedience, and what not; wherein, after we be once plunged ouer head and eares, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runne with the guylt of many ſinnes, then will <hi>Sathan</hi> lay about him, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his buſines like a moſt valiant Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, to catch vs in the moſt dangerous ſnare of all other, euen deepe Deſpaire: Hee will challenge our ſoules by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere iuſtice of God, let vs ſay againſt him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2677:19"/> whatſoeuer we can, and argue againſt him as long as we will, yet will he inſult, reioyce, and reply, ſaying: Neither Gods mercies, nor Chriſtes merites, can any thing helpe, but thou muſt needs be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſo lightly heretofore haſt thou eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med God, and his preceptes;<note place="margin">What the Diuell will obiect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, to bring vs to deſpaire.</note> ſo ſmally haſt thou regarded <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> and his merites, or rather ſo willingly, wittingly, and ſeeingly, haſt thou vilipended, and contemned them; and ſo obſtinatly, careleſly, and deſperately, troden them vnder foote, that euen as thou hitherto haſt made no reckoning of God, and haſt not opened the doore of thy heart to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him, and giue him entertainement when he ſtoode without &amp; knocked to be letten in there; ſo now God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite thee with <hi>legetalionis,</hi> with like for like: hee will make no reckoning of thee, hee will not open his eares vnto thee when thou cryeſt vnto him, hee will not let thee haue though thou aske, hee will not let thee finde though thou ſeeke, hee will not open vnto thee though thou knocke. Behold now art thou toſſed like waues of the Sea, thy Fayth wauereth betweene Hope &amp; Dread, and therefore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2677:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2677:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2677:21"/> canſt thou receiue nothing at the Lordes handes: with theſe and infinite ſuch like diſputations, will <hi>Sathan</hi> ſet vpon, &amp; vexe the very elect of God, to bring them (if it were poſſible) to Deſperation. And if the elect ſhall be thus ſitted, (as <hi>Peter</hi> was) in what caſe then ſhall the wicked and reprobate be?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER. IIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond cauſe of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</note>THe ſecond cauſe of Deſperation, is ignorance of God, and want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the will of God, vnto mankind reuealed by his holy word: for as igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Scriptures,<note place="margin">Math 22.</note> as it was pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the mouth of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> himſelfe ſpeaking againſt the <hi>Saduces,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 king. 17.26 pſal. 35.10 11 Prou. 28.29.30.31. Eſa. 1.34. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. 47. Epheſ. 4.18.</note> concerning the reſurrection of the dead, was the cauſe of that their ſo great errour; Euen like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the ignorance of God, is oftentimes the occaſion and cauſe of Gods heauie diſpleaſure; and ſo of diuers and ſundrie inconueniences and miſchiefes:<note place="margin">Bern. ſuper Cant.</note> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, it is alſo a cauſe of this curſed Deſperation, as writeth S. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tra<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cognitio dei ſcilicet et tui, tibi neceſſaria eſt ad ſalutem, quia de ignorantia
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2677:21"/> tui venit ſuperbia, ac de dei ignorantia venit deſperatio.</hi> The knowledge both of God, and of thy ſelfe are neceſſarie vnto ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe out of the ignorance of thy ſelfe, aryſeth pride; and likewiſe out of the ignoraunce of God, commeth Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration. Out of this ignoraunce of God, muſt Deſperation needes ariſe:<note place="margin">Ignorance the mother of Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> for how can it otherwiſe be, but that hee that is altogether without any knowledge of God, muſt deſpaire to receiue any good thing of him? For as no man can take pleaſure nor any profite by hid and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen Treaſure: ſo no man can looke for grace, mercie, and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, or any other benefite or good gift at his handes, of whom he is vtterly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt, &amp; of whom he hath no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER. V.</head>
               <p>THe third Cauſe of Deſperation is the great ſeruitude or bondage of ſinne:<note place="margin">The third cauſe of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</note> with which, who ſoeuer is clogged, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth thereby the Seruant of ſinne; <hi>Iohn 8.34.</hi> And the wofull and hurtfull ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes of ſinnes, are the procurements of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2677:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> Gods curſſes and plagues vpon bodyes,<note place="margin">The wofull and hurtfull effectes of ſinnes.</note> ſoules, landes, children, ſtocke, croppe, and euery thing els that a man hath, or goeth about, at home or abroad, in towne or in fielde, in citie or in countrie, by land or by Water. <hi>Deut 28. Leuit. 26.</hi> Sinne hardeneth the heart. <hi>Heb. 3.13.</hi> It fighteth againſt the Soule. <hi>1. Pet. 2.11.</hi> It gnaweth and tormenteth the conference. <hi>1 Sam. 25.31.</hi> And ſo bringeth men into the moſt damnable gulfe of Deſperation, wherein multitudes of Worldlinges, Matcheuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>picures, and impious Atheiſtes are dayly implunged, and irreuocably drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER. VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fourth ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe of deſperation.</note>THe Fourth cauſe of Deſperation do many gather to themſelues vpon the wordes of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Math. 7.13. Strait is the gate, and narrow is the way that leadeth vnto life, and few there be that finde it.</hi> And againe out of <hi>Math 20.16. Many are called, but few are choſen.</hi> And againe out of <hi>Luke 13.24. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> e to enter in at the ſtraite gate, for many, Lay vnto you, will ſeeke to enter in, and ſhall not be able:</hi> All which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2677:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> places do plainely teach, that few ſhall be ſaued; for in bidding to ſtriue to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in, <hi>Chriſt</hi> giueth vs to vnderſtand that it is not an eaſie matter, but a matter that requireth great ſtrife, paynes, and earneſt diligence againſt the World, the Fleſh, and the Diuell.</p>
               <p>Vpon theſe conſiderations,<note place="margin">The feare and doubt of many.</note> many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to feare, and to tremble, to ſtagger, and to doubt, whether they may thinke themſelues to be in the number of thoſe few that ſhalbe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed yea or no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſo are drawne into Deſpaire, whiles that they find this preſent euill world againſt them with all the baytes, ſnares, ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es, and lettes, pleaſures, and profites thereof, to catch them, letter them, and entangle them, whiles they finde their owne fleſh,<note place="margin">The great &amp; manifold aduerſari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s to mans ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, all which the Diuell vſeth as meanes to drawmen into deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> their owne corrupted nature againſt them; their reaſon poyſoned, their willes and affections blinded, their naturall wiſedome, concupiſences, and luſtes, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring ſtrength to <hi>Sathans</hi> temptations, taking part againg them, dayly &amp; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly ready to betray them into his hands, whiles that they ſee and perceiue euen legions of Diuels, euen all the Diuels in Hell againſt them, with all their craftie
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2677:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2677:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2677:24"/> heads, marueilous ſtrength, infinite wiles, cunning deuiſes, deepe ſleightes, &amp; tryed temptations, lying in ambuſhe againſt their poore ſoules; and who ſeeth not that thouſands are caried hedlong to deſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion through the temptations of either the world, the fleſh, or the Diuell. And thus are we poore wretches in a moſt pittifull caſe aſſaulted &amp; betrayed, on euery ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER. VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fift cauſe of deſperation.</note>THe fift cauſe of Deſperation aryſeth from the manifold croſſes &amp; afflictions of this preſent life: for from hence it is that ſome men being dayly ferrited, follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed on, and euen almoſt preſſed downe with temporall afflictions &amp; troubles,<note place="margin">Sundry kindes of croſſes and afflictions.</note> as penu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, pouertie, hunger, nakednes, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of body, troubles of minde, vnquiet ſuggeſtions of the fleſh, temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Diuell, perſecutions, impriſonments, loſſe of friendes, loſſe of goodes, loſſe of good name &amp; fame, a wicked, crooked, and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward mate in matrimonie, diſobedient &amp; vntoward children, vnkind &amp; vnthankful friends, vndeſerued malice, enuie, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of frowarde neighbours, and many
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2677:24"/> other ſuch like croſſes, as dayly in one ſort or other befal men: When they once feele them ſelues touched &amp; tryed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, anone they take occaſion hereby to cry out, and lamentably to howle,<note place="margin">Ierem. 20.</note> and curſſe the day wherein they where borne, to call that an vnhappy hower wherein their mothers brought them foorth,<note place="margin">Ierem. 15.</note> to wiſh they had died in their birth,<note place="margin">Iob. 3.</note> and that they had periſhed ſo ſoone as they came out of their mothers wombe; that ſome hill might fall vpon them &amp; ouerwhelme them, that ſo they might ſhortly be rid out of their paines: Yea they will not be perſwaded that theſe thinges are ſent of God (for the moſt part) to ſuch as he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, but rather to ſuch as he hateth; and that neuer a louing Father will handle his children ſo as they are handled. Now the Diuell moſt ſubtilly lying in wayte for his aduantage, taketh hold on this their weakneſſe, and ſtriueth by little and litle by ſuch occaſions as theſe to worke vtter deſperation in them; and by theſe meanes oftentimes forceth ſome to ſome ſodaine, wretched, and deſperat endes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:2677:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſixt cauſe of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</note>THe Sixt cauſe of Deſperation is long cuſtome of ſinne, whereby a man yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and ſubmitteth himſelfe as an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and ready bondſlaue to the Diuell, little reſpecting, if not vtterly contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning both God and his word, whoſe dull conſcience through giuing himſelfe ouer to impuritie &amp; filthineſſe of life, is waxed hard in iniquitie, and corrupt wayes, and as it were burned with a hote Iron, ſo that he is now paſt all ſenſe and feeling of ſin, and this long cuſtome groweth as it were into a ſecond nature (in proceſſe of time) which to expell is a matter of great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie.<note place="margin">Long cuſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tome: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th into a ſecond na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> This is it which the Prophet <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi> meant, where he affirmed that it is as hard a thing for ſuch to doe any good that haue beene continually inured with do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of euill, as it is to waſh a Blacka-Moore or Aethiopian skinne white: or to chaunge the ſpots of a Leopard: And therefore according to our Engliſh adage, as that which is bred in the bone, will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer lightly out of the fleſh: ſo an olde wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or long cuſtome of any vice, be it of lying,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2677:25"/> ſwearing, gaming, drinking, whooring, or any other ſuch like, will ſeldome or neuer be remedied: whereby it oftentimes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe, that in the end the Diuel by this meanes hauing laide a foundation ſo ſitting his purpoſe to worke on, bringeth his olde cuſtomers to diſpaire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The firſt Chapter concerning the Remedies againſt the temptations and aſsaultes of Sathan, being the firſt ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l cauſe of Deſperation, before intre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed of in Chap. 3.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>TO meete with the dangerous and manifold temptations of <hi>Sathan,</hi> that great enemie of mankinde, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he continually after other ſinnes firſt committed, laboreth to bring vs into the deepe gulph of Deſperation; It ſhall not be amiſſe, nay rather it ſhall be our beſt courſe and remedie, to learne and practiſe that moſt ſure, ſafe, and excellent counſaile, which the holy Ghoſt giueth by thoſe two worthy Apoſtles of our Sauiour Chriſte <hi>S. Paule</hi> and <hi>S. Iam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Iam. 4.</note>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2677:26"/> whereof <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Saint Paule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>S.</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>nſt the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>kes of Sathan.</note> 
                  <hi>Put on the whole armour of God, that yee may be able to ſtand againſt the aſſaultes of the Diuel &amp;c S. Iames</hi> ſayth, <hi>Reſiſt the Diuell, and he will ſlee from you:</hi> that is to ſay, wee muſt ſtriue againſt all vnlawfull and forbidden luſtes by which he eggeth, draweth, and haleth men from ſinne to ſinne, from bad to worſe, and finally to Deſperation, the worſt of all ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Had <hi>Cain</hi> thus reſiſted the Diuell, he had neuer been ſo far drawen (as he was) from faythleſſe hipocriſie, to enuie; from enuie to murther, and from murther to Deſperation. Had <hi>Iudas</hi> the traytor thus re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>d the Diuell when he by his entiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment firſt yeelded to couetouſneſſe, and ſo for a litle filthy lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re to betray his moſt louing, gentle, and kind Lord &amp; maiſter, he had not from thoſe ſinnes one in the necke of an other finally fallen into deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, wherin he became his owne hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, to the euerlaſting teſtimonie of his owne damnation.</p>
               <p>Full worthy therefore, and very need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in this caſe, is <hi>S. Iames</hi> his counſaile, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ll. &amp;c.</hi> yea and that in the beginning.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:2677:26"/>
               <p>And <hi>S. Paule</hi> goeth further on with the like good counſaile,<note place="margin">A deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the maner of armour wherewith Saint Paule would haue Chriſtians to reſiſt the Diuell.</note> and ſetteth downe very plainely, with what maner of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour he would haue Chriſtians to buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle and furniſh themſelues with, that ſo they may be found the more readie and able to encounter their generall enemies temptations: As firſt, with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritie,</hi> or <hi>Trueth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moure to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell with.</note> which is in the arming of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with true and ſinceere knowledge of God. <hi>Tit. 1.1.</hi> In the true ſeruice of God without hypocriſie, in <hi>Spirit and trueth. Ioſua. 24.14. Ioh. 4.24. 3. Kin. 2.4.</hi> And likewiſe with vpright true ſpeaking and dealing with our neighboures, in word and deed. <hi>Epheſ. 4.25. Exod. 23.1.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">The ſecond kinde of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moure wherewith the Diuell is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted.</note> with the <hi>Breaſt-plate of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe:</hi> that is, with the earneſt apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and endeuoring of our ſelues to all vertue and godlyneſſe in our liues and conuerſations: Where note, that the Apoſtle hauing placed <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritie, Trueth,</hi> or true knowledge of God, in the firſt place: in very fit and good rancke and order, he placed this <hi>Righteouſneſſe;</hi> that is to ſay, practiſe of true knowledge in holynes of life in the ſecond place; as a godly Father
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2677:27"/> herevpon hath very wel obſerued in theſe wordes: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>era dei cognitione &amp; animi ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritate, &amp; puritate primum, deinde pia et ſancta vita <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> debent Chriſtiani milites:</hi> Chriſtian Souldiers ought firſt to haue their heartes and mindes decked and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with true knowledge of God, with true ſinceritie and puritie of minde; and ſecondly, with godly &amp; holy life anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to their true knowledge. Hereby all ſleightie cunning and forcible entries vnto <hi>Sathans</hi> engines and ſubtile ſnares, ſhalbe debarred and ſhut vp: hereby all the paſſages of our thoughts and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations ſhall be preuented and taken vp, that he ſhall not ſo eaſily find any breach or weake place to inuade.<note place="margin">Wereby the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uel is em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened to tempt, and whereby on the other ſide he is diſcouraged and reſiſted.</note> For as on the one ſide, by loſenes and licentiouſnes of the fleſh, by leawdnes of our liues, by our iniquitie and vngodlines, the Diuell is an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ated, fleſhed, and emboldened, dayly to tempt and aſſault vs: for he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the corrup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of our nature a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes to wickedneſſe, he bloweth the bellowes, and kindleth the flame of our bad inclination; hee ſtirreth vs vp, and pricketh vs forward, till after the heaping vp of one ſinne after an other, at t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2677:27"/> length he caſteth vs down headlong into the bottomleſſe pit of Deſperation: So on the other ſide, by this Armour of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, ſinceritie, and integritie of an holy life, is the Diuell withſtood and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, and wee become the more able to ſtand faſt in the day of our temptation: So that it is not without iuſt cauſe, that the Apoſtle compareth this <hi>Righteou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nes,</hi> the ſecond kind of ſpiritual Armour, vnto a corporall <hi>Breaſt-plate;</hi> for that like as a Breaſt-plate ſaueth and fenceth the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall partes of man, as his heart, liuer, and entrailes;<note place="margin">The good fruites of vprightnes, and holine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of life.</note> which once being ſtriken and pierced, mans life is loſt: ſo doth vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and holineſſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, preſerue the heart and conſcience of man free and ſafe from the inuaſion and confuſion wrought by <hi>Sathan,</hi> from the ſicrie dartes of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie, hardneſſe of conſcience, coldneſſe in religion, wickedneſſe of life, corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in conuerſation and finally from Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, the very vpſhot of al miſchiefes.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">The third kind of Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mour for a Chriſtian againſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.</note> muſt we arme and furniſh our ſelues to reſiſt <hi>Sathan</hi> the Diuell, with the <hi>Goſpell of peace,</hi> that is, our heartes muſt be throughly acquainted, and fully fraugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the knowledge of that glad
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2677:28"/> tydings of great ioy, which the Angels of the Lord brought at the birth of <hi>Chriſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 2.10.</note> that tydinges of great ioy, which muſt be vnto all Nations, with that moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and ioyfull embaſſage of the Reconciliation of Man with God, which may full well be called the <hi>Goſpell of peace,</hi> for that it onely maketh the Conſcience of man quiet, and at peace with God, and it ſelfe: then the which, what one thing in all the world, can ſet a man more free from all Deſperation?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fourth Armour. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor. 16.13</note>Fourthly, with <hi>Fayth in Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> wherewith the ſame <hi>S. Paule</hi> arming men againſt ſpirituall aſſaultes by <hi>Sathan</hi> and his miniſters, and preparing them to the ſpirituall battle againſt the Diuell and his members, encourageth them not to ſhrinke, but to cleaue faſt to this Fayth, whereby we may reſiſt and beate backe our ſpirituall enemie.</p>
               <p>And likewiſe <hi>S. Peter</hi> inſtructing vs to prepare and make our ſelues ſtrong, to encounter with the common enemie the Diuell, teacheth vs to reſiſt him by Fayth eſpecially:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Pet. 5.8</note> 
                  <hi>Be ſober</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>and watch, for your aduerſarie the Diuell, goeth about ſeeking whom he may deuowre, whom reſist
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2677:28"/> ſtedfaſt in the fayth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For this cauſe <hi>Saint Baſil</hi> vpon the <hi>32.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baſilius in Pſalm. 32.</note> Pſalme ſayth, <hi>What man is able to wage warre with the Diuell, vnleſse he flee for helpe to the Captaine of the Hoaſt through Fayth in him, to wound and thruſt through his enemie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And likewiſe <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> accounted this Fayth to be ſo powerfull,<note place="margin">Augu. lib 3. Cap. 20. de lib. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bi trio</note> 
                  <hi>that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth, vanquiſheth, and ouercommeth the Diuell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this true Chriſtian Fayth which is of ſuch power as is aforeſayd,<note place="margin">What fayth is.</note> is a ſure truſt in the mercie of God the Father, through the merites of <hi>Christ Ieſus,</hi> when we do perſwade our ſelues moſt certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye of the pardon of our ſinnes through <hi>Chriſtes</hi> righteouſnes; and of eternall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation by his paſsion, hereby obtayning peace in our conſcienſes with God, and reſt, and walke in obedience to his will and commaundements by his word vnto vs reuealed. Of this kind of Fayth is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated in <hi>Abac. 2.4. Rom. 3.28. Rom. 5.1. Epheſ. 2.8.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fift kinde of Armour to reſiſt the Diuell with,<note place="margin">The fift kind of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moure.</note> whereof <hi>S. Paul</hi> in the cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of a Chriſtian Souldiers armour maketh rehearſall, is the <hi>Word of God:</hi> this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2677:29"/> is the Sworde of the Spirit, whereby the ſuggeſtions and wicked temptations of <hi>Sathan,</hi> are beaten backe, propelled, and kept off, euen as a man keepeth backe his enemie at the poynt of his Sword.</p>
               <p>With this kinde of Armour did our chiefe captaine <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> in his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood heere on earth, reſiſt and put backe all the Diuell his ſubtil and falſe tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, anſwering euery one of them with <hi>Scriptum eſt,</hi> It is written: Whence wee may learne by the like meanes,<note place="margin">Chriſt him ſelfe an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> how to reſiſt the Diuels temptations</note> after his moſt excellent example, to combat with the D uell, and to giue him the foyle, when ſoeuer by him, or any his wicked inſtruments, wee ſhall be tempted to this Deſperation, or any other ſinnes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſouer.</p>
               <p>If wee be tempted to ſweare and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the holy name of God, it is to be reſiſted with <hi>Scriptum est,</hi> It is written, <hi>Thou ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine.</hi> If to pollute and breake the Lords Saboath day through either labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring about our pleaſures or profites, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, It is written <hi>Remember that thou keep holy. &amp;c.</hi> If to murther, and ſhedding of blood, by any forbidden way or meanes,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2677:29"/> or vpon any vnlawfull occaſion what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſwere, It is written, <hi>Thou ſhalt do no murther.</hi> If to ſteale and purloyne by any vnlawfull meanes, directly or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ractly; anſwere, It is witten, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</hi> If we be tempted to Vſurie,<note place="margin">Exod. 22.25. Deut 23.19. Leuit. 25.37 Pſalm. 15.5.</note> let vs draw out this Sword of the Spirit, <hi>Thou ſhalt not giue to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurie vnto thy brother, Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of monie, Vſurie of meate, or of any other thing.</hi> If he mooue vs to deceipt and frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent dealing, let vs reſiſt him with, It is written,<note place="margin">1. Theſ 4.5. Leuit. 25.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Let no man oppreſse or deceaue his brother in bargoning, for the Lord is a Iudge in ſuch thinges.</hi> If we be ſollicited to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyaltie, and diſobedience to Princes, let vs ſtriue againſt that, with, It is written, <hi>Let euery Soule be ſubiect to the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. &amp;.</hi> Finally to be ſhort,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.2.3.</note> to what kinde of ſinne, miſchiefe, or inconuenience ſo euer any of vs all ſhall hoppen to be dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, intiſed, or inueigled,<note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſtore of ſwordes againſt eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kind of temptation.</note> let vs ſearch the Scriptures, and we ſhall ſoone finde ſtoore of Swordes, of one kind or other to anſwere, foyle, and recoyle, what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer this mortall enemie of ours can vſe or obiect againſt vs: heere is armour enough to find him occupied with.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:2677:30"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſixt kinde of Chriſtian armour.</note>The ſixt kinde of ſpirituall Armour, and heauenly furniture, wherewith <hi>Saint Paule,</hi> or rather the Holy Ghoſt by <hi>Saint Paule,</hi> would haue vs complet and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed againſt all the dangerous combats, conflictes, and wicked ſuggeſtions of this wicked and damned ſpirite, thereby to auoyde, repell, &amp; vanquiſh him vtterly, is deuoure, heartie, zelous, &amp; godly prayer. Ouer and beſides <hi>S. Paule</hi> his inſtruction, and moſt needfull exhortation, in this caſe his and our Lord, Maiſter, and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> hath commended vnto vs this kind of weapon, when he taught to pray with this Petition, <hi>And lead vs not into temptation, but deliuer vs from euill.</hi> Let vs then apply this Armour, this kind of propulſatiue weapon, and feruently and heartely vſe it: And firmely beleeue that which <hi>Dauid</hi> the Prophet for our good encouragement hath written in <hi>Pſa. 145.19. God is neere: to thoſe which call vpon him, and will fulfill the deſire of them that feare him, and deliuer them.</hi> Whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer therefore we are tempted, allured, and drawen on by <hi>Sathan</hi> through coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe to riches, through ambition to honour, through enuie to murther,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2677:30"/> through concupiſence to adultry, through intemperance to gluttony; or to be ſhort through any other ſinne to iniquitie. Let vs ſtraight wayes by prayer, craue for power and ſtrength from aboue, to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come theſe temptations, and eſpecially the moſt dangerous ſuggeſtion of Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire.</p>
               <p>This kind of Armour is alwayes ready at hand, ſo that <hi>Sathan</hi> can no ſooner at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing againſt vs, but this wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon is as ſoone ready (if we heartely and zelouſly lay hold thereon) to repell and vanquiſh all his practiſes againſt vs: And therefore, <hi>Pray, pray, pray.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The ſecond Chapter concerning remedies and helpes againſt Ignorance, the ſecond cauſe of Deſperation, entreated of before in Chapter. IIII.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>COncerning the Second cauſe of Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, to wit, Ignoraunce; Our Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> who was nothing ignoraunt of the manifold miſchiefes, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2677:31"/> of the manifeſt dangers that the Diuell leadeth ſillie men into, as it were blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded through blind Ignoraunce: and he knowing that Ignoraunce is rather the mother of Deſperation (as heretofore in the iiii. Chap. of the Cauſes of Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration hath been ſufficiently prooued,) then of Deuotion, as the Papiſtes haue in this poynt ignorantly taught &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainde: hath in his owne perſon, and with his owne mouth exhorted and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed all men,<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.29.</note> to <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> which is a leſſon in this caſe moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for all men, to learne thereby to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer themſelues out of the dangerous gulfe of Ignoraunce, and ſo conſequently out of many other ſinnes, and finally out of Deſperation; whereinto thouſandes through Ignoraunce, haue been implun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and drowned for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Remedies againſt Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance.</note>Let vs therefore for the remedie and auoyding of finall Deſperation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto ſo many runne headlong through Ignoraunce, little knowing, and leſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding what they do, vntill it be too late, receiue the word of God, which (as <hi>S. Iames</hi> ſayth) <hi>Is able to ſaue our ſoules:</hi> with all readines like vnto the Noble men of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2677:31"/> 
                  <hi>Berea,</hi> and ſearch the Scriptures dayly.<note place="margin">Act. 17.11.</note> Let vs ſeeke after the knowledge of God in time, And as the Prophet <hi>Eſai</hi> ſayd,<note place="margin">Eſai. 55.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Seeke the Lord whiles he my be found, and call vpon him whiles he is neare.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The danger of wilfull Ignorance.</note> And let vs be aſſured of this, that all maner of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce is perilous; but wilfull Ignorance, of all other is moſt perilous: For it is (as a learned Writer hath affirmed) a plaine Prognoſtication,<note place="margin">A. D. in the plaine mans path to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</note> and a demonſtratiue ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of eternall death. It is a moſt horrible and a fearefull thing for a man to refuſe Inſtructions, depiſe Counſaile, harden their Heartes, ſtoppe their Eares, &amp; cloſe vp their Eyes againſt God: this is the very vpſhot of euerlaſting ruine.</p>
               <p>Let the Ignorant therefore that ſtande in this dangerous eſtate,<note place="margin">What the Ignorant muſt do.</note> repaire with all diligence and attentiueneſſe vnto the learned Mimiſters &amp; diſpenſers of Gods moſt ſacred word, and at their mouthes enquire the knowledge of Gods Lawes. This doth God himſelfe commaunde vs by the Prophet <hi>Malachie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Malach. 4.</note> And when we feele our Conſciences wounded, let vs, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the example of the godly, faythfull, and deuout people, who after the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Gods word preached, came vnto
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2677:32"/> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, ſaying, <hi>Men and brethren,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act 2.</note> 
                  <hi>what ſh l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> we do?</hi> Euen thus I ſay, let vs come vnto Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,<note place="margin">Counſaile for the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant very neceſſarie.</note> and confeſſe and acknowledge our great blindnes and ignoraun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſay vnto them, Helpe vs, inſtruct vs, teach vs, ſet vs in the way, &amp; guide vs in the pathes of the knowledge of God, and of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: for ſurely they are the Phiſitions and Surgions of our ſoules,<note place="margin">Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> worde are.</note> ſo that if we repaire vnto them, they ſhall giue vs to drinke of the holſome Waters of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to quench our thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t of Ignorance: they are the di p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncers of the mani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olde graces of God, and the Lords Stewardes to giu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> each one of vs our portions in due time.</p>
               <p>We haue not <hi>Chriſt</hi> alwayes amongſt vs (as appertayning to his bodely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.) but as himſelfe ſayth, we haue <hi>the Po re</hi> alwayes amongſt vs: Euen ſo alſo we haue not <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe (that body I meane, which ſitteth at the right hand of God the father) alwayes with vs: but yet our Lord <hi>Chriſt,</hi> aſcending vp on high, gave vnto men among other gifts, this gift alſo (if we could rightly conſider of it) of no ſmal value, euen Paſtors &amp; Doctors;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2677:32"/> that is, the Miniſters of the Goſpell of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that might inſtruct, informe, and teach vs in the way of life, that might declare vnto v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſecret counſailes and hidden myſteries of God, that might arme vs with the <hi>Sword of the ſpirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">How the true mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of gods word are to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of.</note> which is the word of God, to encounter &amp; reſiſt our deadly enemie the Diuell therewith. Let vs ioyfully receaue rhem; for who ſo receaueth them as they ought to be, receaueth alſo with them, him that ſent them, whoſe Meſſengers they are: Let vs heare them, for they bring vnto vs the word of life: Let vs giue credite vnto the Lords Miniſters, and Glorie vnto the Lord himſelfe, that hath giuen in his great loue this bleſsing vnto vs, to haue his Meſſengers and Ambaſſadours aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding among vs, to declare and make knowen vnto vs by them, what his owne good will and pleaſure is in all thinges, to the auoyding of this blind Ignorance, the very mother of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſperation, and ſo conſequently of eternall Damnation with the author thereo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and his curſed Angels for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:2677:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the great ſeruitude and bondage of ſinnes, and of the remedies thereof.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>Concerning the great ſeruitud &amp; bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of ſinne, being the third (before noted) cauſe of Deſperation, for the helps and remedies thereof this haue I briefly to ſay, that what though we haue been ſeruaunts vnto ſinne, and haue been preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſurpreſſed with the bondage thereof, ſo that we muſt needes confeſſe, (vnleſſe we ſhould prooue our ſelues ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, and that there were no trueth in vs) that we through our often doing of thoſe thinges which we ſhould not haue done; and on the other ſide, through our leauing off thoſe things vndone which we ſhould haue done, haue moſt iuſtly deſerued Gods threatened curſſes and plagues to light on our bodyes, our ſoules, our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, our ſtockes, our croppes, and euery thing els we go about, and put our hands vnto. What though our ſinnes fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſoules, and gnaw our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and be ready euen out of hand to lead vs into the moſt dangerous ſtate of Deſperation? What though we haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and fallen out with our brethren?
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2677:33"/> as did <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Examples tending to the ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening of our fayth, hope, &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</note> who were ſo h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at in contention one againſt an other, that they forſooke one anothers compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in high diſpleaſure and heate of their ſtomackes, the one taking with him <hi>Luke,</hi> the other <hi>Iohn?</hi> What though we haue yeelded vnto, practiſed, and followed Oppreſsion, Extortion, polling, pilling, and wreſting what we can by hooke or crooke from our brethren?<note place="margin">Luke. 19.2.</note> So did <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus,</hi> yet notwithſtanding after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, his forſaking and ceaſſing from bad getting, his reſtitution, and almes giuing, receiued that moſt chearefull and comfortable ſaying of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luke. 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>This day is ſaluation entred into thine houſe.</hi> What though we haue been Theeues, robbers and ſtealers of our neighbours goodes? ſo was the Theefe that was crucified with <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and yet vpon his humble, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite, and ſorrowfull confeſsion of his ſinnes, he heard this moſt ſweete word from Chriſt, <hi>This day ſhalt thou be with mee in Paradiſe.</hi> What though we haue murthered and ſhead the blood, or cauſed the blood to be ſhed of ſome of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? ſo did <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rias,</hi> and yet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his zealous, inward, &amp; true vnfained
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2677:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſorrowfulnes and repentance, he was not taken away in his ſinne, but found par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. And ſo did the Iewes which put to death the Lord of life.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Manaſses</hi> was an Idolater, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed the Temple of God, he withſtood and did beat downe the trueth, he ſet vp Idolatrie,<note place="margin">2. Kin. 21.</note> he was a Coniurer and a South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayer, he ſhed a boundance of Innocent blood, ſo that the ſtreetes flowed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, he committed more abhominations then the <hi>Cananites</hi> or <hi>Amorites</hi> whom for their filthineſt the Lord cut off out of the land of the liuing; he ſacrificed his ſonnes and daughters to Diuels: and yet vpon his true returning to the Lord from the bottome of his heart, he found fauoure and mercie,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. Chro. 33.</note>If our ſinnes then, or the ſinnes of any one of vs, were as greeuous as euer were the ſinnes of <hi>Manaſses,</hi> yet vpon our true and vnfaigned returne to the Lord, ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we deſpaire of his mercie? ſhall we, or may we, or dare we thinke that the mercie and power of the Lod is ſhorte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? or that God is not the ſame God he was? Is he not as readie to pardon
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2677:34"/> and forgiue ſinnes, the ſinnes of a man repenting, returning, and faythfully cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon him, as euer he was the ſinnes of <hi>Manaſſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe examples, and many more, are written for our learning, comfort, and ſtrengthening of our fayth; hope, and patience, that we ſhould in no wiſe deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire vpon our true repentance, neither for the multitude, nor greeuouſneſſe of our ſinnes.</p>
               <p>And likewiſe alſo it is written for the bruſing, and as it were euen for the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the backe of all damnable. Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, and to hold the heartes, and to reſtore the faynting and dullie ſprites of all ſuch as the ſeruitude and bondage of ſinne, this our third cauſe of Deſperation doth vexe and preſſe downe: It is (I ſay) written,<note place="margin">Luk. 9.56.</note> that the <hi>Sonne of man is come to ſaue mens liues.</hi> And he him ſelfe hath ſayd, <hi>I am come to call not the iuſt, but ſinners.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 10. Math. 20. Ioh. 3. Wherefore Chriſt can into this world.</note> And againe, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt is come to giue his life a redemption for many.</hi> Alſo, <hi>God the Father hath not ſent his S nne to iudge the Worlde, but to the ende the Worlde may be ſaued by him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:2677:35"/>
               <p>Now what is it to ſaue, &amp; not to iudge? but to deliuer from death and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; wherein we lay in the middeſt of the bondage of ſinne; for ſinne is the death and damnation of the ſoule: Now he can not ſaue vs except ſinne be firſt taken from vs; And therefore, and for this cauſe came <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> the Sonne of God,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note> and he hath declared himſelfe to the world, to the end that he ſhould take away ſinnes, and ſhould deſtroy the workes of the Diuell. If it be ſo that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> be come into the world to take away ſinnes; and if the ſame were his intent and his meſſage, the purpoſe of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> ſhall not fayle at all, and his meſſage remayneth ſtedfaſt and true; he then without all doubt, hath taken away this which the Diuell would perſwade vs to be a cauſe of Deſperation, this great ſeruitude and bondage of ſinne, from all thoſe that truſt in him, and do verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue and perſwade themſelues in the bottome of their conſciences that it is moſt true: but yet how comes this to paſſe? to wit, by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> onely, by his owne free grace and mercie; by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites and merites of himſelfe, who is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2677:35"/> our onely Sauiour,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.29.</note> without any other meane or merit; for he is the only <hi>Lambe of God, which taketh away the ſinnes of the worlde.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 4.12.</note> As alſo <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſayd to the Iewes, <hi>There is none other ſaluation, but onely in Ieſus Chriſt; for among men there is giuen none other name vnder heauen whereby wee muſt be ſaued.</hi> And ſo Chriſt himſelfe ſayd after he was ryſen from the dead. <hi>It muſt needes haue been, that Chriſt muſt haue ſuffered death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk 24.44.</note> 
                  <hi>and that he muſt haue ryſen the third day from the dead, and that amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of life, and forgiueneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of ſinnes muſt be preached in his name to all people, and to all nations.</hi> O how ſweete and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table are theſe wordes and ſayinges of God, which is the onely eternall trueth in deed? O how worthy are they to be layde vp in the deapth of our hearts, and to haue our whole confidence repoſed freely vpon them.<note place="margin">Colloſſ 2.</note> And to the <hi>Colloſsians</hi> it is ſayd, <hi>God hath quickened vs which were dead in ſinnes with Ieſus Chriſt, forgiuing vs all our treſpaſſes, and hath put out the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing that was against vs, hee euen tooke it out of the way, and faſtened it on the Croſse.</hi> What meaneth he by this, but onely that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> hath taken away the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2677:36"/> of our debt? to wit, that we did owe for our ſinnes, and hath taken it and tyde it with him ſelfe vpon the Croſſe, and hath in deed payde it full bitterly: who alſo is for vs, and will ſurely take away this great ſeruitude &amp; bondage of ſinne, (which the Diuell would vſe as an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Deſperation againſt vs) in caſe we will beleeue his word, and that we can ſettle out mindes, and quiet our harts, to account and eſteeme his bitter paſſion and merites to be ſo great and of ſuch value, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they are able, effect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all, and of ſufficient ſtrength, to obtaine theſe aforeſayd thinges for vs. And <hi>Chriſtes</hi> prayer to his heauenly Father is heard, and remayneth heard continually when he prayed,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o. 17, 20.</note> ſaying, <hi>I p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y not for theſe alone,</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaning his there preſent Diſciples) <hi>but for them al o which ſhall beleeue in mee through their worde:</hi> Wherefore the ſame prayer includeth euery one of vs, ſo farre foorth as we beleeue, and place the ſame in our heartes, and wholly repoſe our ſelues thereon.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct 10.42.43.</note>And <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſayth, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs to preach vnto the pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, and to test<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fie th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t it is hee that is ordayned of God a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2677:36"/> Iudge of the quicke and the dead, and that to him al the Prophets giue witneſse that through his name all that beleeue, ſhould receiue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer, <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.21.</note> 
                  <hi>God hath made him which knew no ſinne, ſinne for vs, to the ende that we ſhould be made the righteouſneſse of God in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And heere is to be noted,<note place="margin">What ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth at our handes.</note> what Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, or Iuſtice and Goodneſſe that is, which God requireth and eſteemeth; which is no other, but that onely which dwelleth and holdeth vpon the Iuſtice, Goodneſſe, and Merite of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> being vtterly ignoraunt of the Iuſtice, or R ghteouſneſſe and Goodneſſe which many do ſeek in their owne good works.</p>
               <p>But yet when I ſtande ſo much vppon this poynt, to prooue that our ſinnes ſhould be no cauſe of Deſperation, (a thing which the Diuell greatly vrgeth &amp; obiecteth againſt the conſcience of an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant man) for that our ſinnes are taken away by the innocent Lambe <hi>Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> that he hath ſufficiently pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome therof, &amp; that we are become righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous by the righteouſnes of <hi>I ſus Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t,</hi> it is not here my meaning, neither would
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2677:37"/> I haue any man ſo to miſtake mee, and miſvnderſtande mee, that I thinke, or would haue any other men to thinke hereby, that there is no more ſinne in vs, or that ſinne dwelleth not in theſe our mortall bodyes:<note place="margin">Sinne dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth euen in the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and in the moſt righteous men in the world: but yet raigneth not in them</note> for I confeſſe it plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and it is too true, that ſinne indeede dwelleth in vs; but yet to the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of an afflicted conſcience againſt Deſperation I affirme it (hauing the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures for my teachers herein) that although the roote of ſinne, the naughtie diſpoſition, and inclination to ſinne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth alwayes ſtrong in a Chriſtian, and neuer can be wholly vanquiſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we put off by death, this ſinfull fleſh of ours; although (I ſay) it do dwell in vs, yet it doth not raigne in any Chriſtian beleeuer; yet it is not able to damne a true faythfull beleeuer: It can not (I ſay) damne vs, for as much as we are in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and that we do fight and ſtriue againſt the remanent of ſinne, albeit we ſtagger and wauer ſometimes, and do feele and perceiue our ſelues to be aſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſometimes by the ſtrong temptations of the Diuell, and the fleſh. This is it that <hi>S. Paule</hi> writeth of when he ſayth, <hi>There
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2677:37"/> is now no dampnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>which walke not after the fleſh but after the ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The remaynent &amp; roote of ſinne dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth alwayes in vs, but wee like vnto li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious worldlinges, giue it not the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and ſuffer it not to range too farre, and to take too deepe a roote, but wee breake it, tame it, and make it ſubiect vnto vs by walking after the ſpirit. &amp;c. and then nothing more ſure then that there ſhalbe no condemnation at all vnto vs thereby, neither any cauſe of Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration thereby, for that we are iuſtified by our Fayth and deliuered from ſinne; to wit, theſe ſinnes which might condemne vs, the roote, originall, and mother of ſinne yet notwithſtanding ſtill aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, remayning, and dwelling in vs; againſt which we warre and ſtriue, as long as we continue in this life; but the victorie remayneth to our Chieftaine &amp; head-Captaine <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> by the law of his ſpirit, which maketh vs to liue in him, and hath ſet vs free from the right of ſinne and death (in ſuch ſort that we may no more feare ſinne, nor death) by <hi>Ieſus Christ,</hi> who hath ouercome all for our
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2677:38"/> wealth, and hath reconciled vs eternally to his Father; who as our deare Father, from hence-foorth will ſhew fauour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, for the loue of <hi>Ieſ s Chriſt</hi> his deare Sonne, and ſo will take from vs all our ſinnes as though we had neuer commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them: Euen ſo doth he promiſe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Mich. 7.18.19.</note> 
                  <hi>God is one God, willing to ſhew vs grace and mercie, hee will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e to vs, and will be fauourable, and hee will t ke away our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, and caſt our ſinnes into the deapth of the Sea.</hi> And againe it is ſayd of Gods won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull mercies, <hi>The Lord is full of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and mercie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.10. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>long ſuffering and of great goodnes: Hee will not alwayes be chyding, neither keepeth he his anger for euer. He hath not dealt with vs after our ſinnes, nor rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs according to our iniquities: For looke how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>igh the Heauen is in compa iſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Earth ſo great is his mercie alſo towards them that feare him Looke how wide a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſo the Faſt is from the Weſt ſo farre hath he ſet our ſinnes from vs. Yea, lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as a Father pittieth his owne children, euen ſo is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lord mercifull vnto them that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>e him: For he knoweth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we be m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e; he remembreth that we are but duſt. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the great mercies of God towardes
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2677:38"/> ſinners, read more in <hi>Pſal. 145 8.9 and 147.8.10</hi> &amp; in <hi>Ioel. 2.13. Math. 18 11. 2. Cor. 1 3.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Places of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſetting foorth gods great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</note> 
                  <hi>Epheſ 2.4. 1. Tim. 1.13.</hi> vnto the <hi>18.</hi> verſe.</p>
               <p>Surely theſe places are wordes of moſt rare and ſingular comfort, and they be certaine, ſinne, ſure, and vnchangeable, ſpoken and pronounced by the eternall veritie it ſelfe, and therfore not to be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted or deſpaired of. But yet let vs take heed, leaſt that verſe be verified in vs,
<q>Stulti dum vitant vitia in contraria currunt.</q> Let vs not abuſe Gods mercies, making a cloake thereof to couer our ſinnes: Let vs not preſume too farre, and ſay as in <hi>Eccleſiasticus 5.6. The mercie of God is great, hee will forgiue my manifolde ſinnes: for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and wrath commeth from him &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:2677:39"/>
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The fourth Chapter concerning the Remedies to be vſed against the Fourth cauſe of Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, aryſing of the doubts ſuggeſted by the Diuell vnto many men to bring them into deſpaire of their ſaluation, by meanes of the ſmall number of thoſe that ſhal be ſaued, in compariſon of the great number of the reprobate.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>GReat in deed is the power, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold and marueilous are the pollicies, deuices, wyles, ſubtilties, aſſaultes, and ſuggeſtions, wherewith and whereby that wylie Foxe,<note place="margin">A catalogue or rehearſall of many thinges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hereby the Diuell craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ily temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth men to ſinne &amp; deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eration.</note> that old bitten Dogge, that ſubtill <hi>Sathan</hi> the Diuell, dayly and howerly practiſeth to entice, allure, and euen as it were to force multitudes of men heere on earth, into one ſinne or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wherevnto he findeth and prooueth them to be naturally enclyned; and laſt of all vpon one occaſion or other, into Deſperation.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l tempteth by riches.</note>If he eſpieth a man to he rich, and to haue worldly bleſſinges through the gift of God, then will he apply him earneſtly
<pb facs="tcp:2677:39"/> by his proſperitie to lull him aſleepe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the forgetfulneſſe of God, in world Pleaſures, pleaſant Vanities, and tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie delights, comfortes, and ſolaces; and by truſting in his Riches to lift vp him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe arrogantly aboue others; to ſwell in pride, &amp; to contemne his brethren, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting (and that with great ſawcineſſe and boldneſſe) many fonde, palpable, and groſſe errours and follies, againſt Gods word, euen as if he ſhould ſay, Who is the Lord?</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, if a man be poore,<note place="margin">How the diuell temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie.</note> he laboreth thereby to make him contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible before the world, to pinch and nipp him with the want of many thinges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie both for backe and bellie, that he ſeeth before his face many others haue in great and in aboundant meaſure:<note place="margin">Prou. 30 9,</note> he ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citeth him to ſteale, to take the name of God in vaine, to ſeeke after gaine by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt, vnlawfull, and vngodly meanes; to murmure, diſtruſt, blaſpheame, and deſpaire.</p>
               <p>If a man haue Friends,<note place="margin">How the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth by friend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Gen. 3.6.</note> he will vſe them as his inſtrumentes, to tempt vnto ſome euill by their leawd &amp; wicked counſaile, as he did procure <hi>Euah</hi> to do vnto <hi>Adam,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2677:40"/> Iob</hi> his Wife to <hi>Iob. Haman</hi> his Wife vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>man.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 2.9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſter. 5.14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth by ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>If thou haſt enemies, then will he pricke thee forward by their proceedinges and dealinges againſt thee, vnto vniuſt cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, wicked anger, and diueliſh reuenge.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth by care<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fulnes.</note>If thou be carefull for thy familie, wife and children, he will take hold vpon that occaſion to ſtuffe thy hart with too much deſire of hauing, and getting by right or by wrong, and therby through extreame couetouſneſſe, make thee to forgoe all godlynes and pietie.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, if thou be careleſſe, that's it that he can make vſe of alſo;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nes.</note> for as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſayth, <hi>Infert diabolus ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>, vt inferat etiam perditionem. &amp;c.</hi> In In heauen Angels became Diuels. In Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Fuah</hi> fell into diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. In the Schole of <hi>Chriſt, Iudas</hi> became a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raytor to his Lord &amp; Maiſter: and all this (ſayth <hi>S. Bernard</hi>) through ſecuritie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etchleſnes to keepe themſelues in that good ſtate wherin they were once ſet.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th by ſtrength, by health, &amp; ablenes of body and beautie.</note>Haſt thou ſtrength? thereby will he t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke occaſion to embolden and harden thee to do iniurie &amp; wrong, &amp; to ſet vpon thy weaker.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:2677:40"/>
               <p>Haſt thou health and a ſtrong able bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die? by thoſe will he induce and entice thee to one kind or other of leawdneſſe and diſſolutneſſe.</p>
               <p>Haſt thou beautie? that will he make an inſtrument for bawdrie; an inticement and an allurement to voluptuouſnes and wanton delightes.</p>
               <p>Haſt thou honour and dignitie in the world?<note place="margin">How the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel tempteth by honor &amp; dignitie.</note> thereby will he blow the bellowes of pride, audacitie and boldneſſe, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, to cruſh, and tread vnder foote thine inferiours.</p>
               <p>Haſt thou Viuacitie,<note place="margin">How the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel tempteth by quicknes of ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it and ſharpnes of wit.</note> or quicknes of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſharpneſſe of witte and learning? theſe alſo will he ſtriue to abuſe &amp; wreſt to ſerue his turne to excogitate, inuent, and deuiſe a thouſand vanities: yea, and all the rare and excellent giftes of God, which God doth beſtow on any man: this Diuell, this arch-enemie of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, will leaue no wayes, nor meanes vnattempted, to procure man to abuſe the ſame to a cleane contrary ende (if it were poſſible) to that for which they were beſtowed.</p>
               <p>And finally, the very Word of God,<note place="margin">How the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempteth by Gods word.</note> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen through Gods great and infinite
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2677:41"/> goodnes, to be our ſpirituall Sword, to reſiſt and encounter the Diuell with; which as <hi>S. Iames</hi> ſayth, <hi>is able to ſaue the ſoules of men:</hi> which as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>is the power of God to ſaluation to euery one that beleeueth:</hi> which as holy <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth, <hi>was a lanterne vnto his feete, and a light vnto his pathes.</hi> This, euen this, will the Diuell ſo farre foorth as euer he may, with all the cunning fetches, craftes, and pollicies that euer he can deuiſe, ſeeke to abuſe, wreſt, and miſapply,<note place="margin">How the Diuell will abu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt, &amp; mis-apply Gods word.</note> from the true meaning ſence and ſignification thereof, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme lyes, vntruethes, and hereſies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by: he will draw ſome textes and ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereof, to bring men into preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their owne Vertues, Woorthines, and Merites, to their vtter ouerthrow. And likewiſe with ſome other places and ſentences thereof, he will beſtirre himſelfe to bring men to wauer in Fayth, to doubt of Gods graces and mercies through <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo finally to fall into vtter deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration. And thus doth he dayly abuſe and wreſt all thoſe places of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures before noted and alledged in the Fourth cauſe of Deſperation, tending to proue the ſmall number of thoſe that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2677:41"/> ſhall be ſaued, in compariſon of the huge and great number of the reprobate.</p>
               <p>Thoſe places I ſay, doth he vrge vpon the conſciences of many in the world, and by his miſapplying of them, and by his miſconſtruing of <hi>Chriſtes</hi> purpoſe, drift, and meaning therein, draweth and dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them to feare and to tremble, to doubt and deſpaire, that they are none of that ſmall number, ſeeing ſo few ſhall be ſaued.</p>
               <p>But ô thou man that art thus tryed, tempted, and drawen towardes tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! for thy remedy and helpe herein, <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> and conſider vpon thoſe places, to what end and purpoſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> delyuered this doctrine, and thou ſhalt anone prooue and finde, that his meaning was nothing leſſe then to driue men into deſpaire,<note place="margin">The true vſe of thoſe Scriptures which the Diuell ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g men to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration thereby.</note> but rather hereby to exhort, perſwade, and to giue caueats, and warning peeces vnto all men that run at randome after the world, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them ſelues, and their dangers, and tickle ſtates; to awake &amp; rouſe them vp that are ſo faſt lulied a ſleepe in the dangerous cradle of ſecuritie, &amp; wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe, that ſo they might be touched,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2677:42"/> mooued and ſtirred vp to embrace in time when time ſerues, a farre more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and watchfull care of their ſaluation, that by ſuch meanes, they may be found in the number of <hi>Chriſtes</hi> little flocke, and of thoſe few that ſhall be ſaued; whom the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> exhorted to <hi>make an end of their ſaluation with feare and trembling:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> by which they might be made more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and more diligent in that their ſo waightie a buſineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Fift Chapter wherein are conteined the comforts, helpes, and remedies againſt the fift cauſe of Deſperation, which is the heauie and great waight of croſſes, afflictions, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and neceſſities, that God ſuffereth to full vpon many in this life.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>MOſt true, moſt notable, and moſt confortable for the diſtreſſed and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted children of God, is that golden ſentence of the holy Ghoſt, penned by his choſen veſſell <hi>S. Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Rom. 8.28. All thinges worke together for the beſt, to them
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2677:42"/> that loue God.</hi> For euen the afflictions and troubles of Gods children are ſo ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied vnto them by the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Heb. 12 10.</note> that by the ſame they are made <hi>pertakers of Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſse.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12 14.</note> By the ſame they enioy the quiet fruite of <hi>Righteouſneſſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.6.</note> By the ſame they attaine vnto a greater meaſure of <hi>Ioy in the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6 14.</note> By the ſame the world is crucified to them, and they to the world. By the ſame they are made conformable to <hi>Chriſtes</hi> death.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.32.</note> By the ſame they are kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the condemnation of the world. By the ſame they learne experience,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.5.</note> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, hope &amp;c.</p>
               <p>So that theſe thinges rightly pondered,<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modites of croſſes and afflictions to Gods children.</note> weighed, and conſidered, their Croſſes are mercies, their loſſes gaynes, their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are their ſchoollinges, and their aduerſitie their learned Vniuerſitie. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde thou <hi>Sathan,</hi> thou canſt not make theſe afflictions croſſes and troubles, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good nor likely cauſes of Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſo they be taken, borne, and vſed as they ought to be, for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for the learning, comfort, helpe, and remedie of all Gods afflicted chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, whom thou woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull gladly perſwade, that their afflictions are ſignes
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2677:43"/> and prognoſticating tokens of Gods wrath; and ſo conſequently if thou coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, thou wouldſt draw them thereby to deſpaire of Gods loue and mercies. It is written I ſay,<note place="margin">Prou. 3.12.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Lord correcteth him whom he loueth, euen as the father doth the child in whom he delighteth.</hi> And againe, <hi>My ſonne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb 12.5, 6, 7, 8, 9. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>deſpiſe not the chaſtening of the Lord, neither faint when thou art rebuked of him, for whom the Lord loueth, he chaſtineth; and he ſcourgeth euery ſonne that he receiueth. If yee endure chaſtening, God offereth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto you, as vnto ſonnes; for what ſonne is it whom the father chaſteneth not? If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yee be without correction, whereof all are partakers, then are yee baſtards, and not ſonnes,</hi> and ſo foorth vnto the 12. verſe. Theſe and many other ſuch like ſayinges and ſentences of the holy Scriptures, are moſt euident teſtimonies, that afflictions, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, croſſes, and vexations, are ſure to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of Gods grace, mercie, and fauour, whereby God aſſureth vs of his mercifull will and fatherly good heart towards vs, and not ſignes of his wrath and heauie diſpleaſure, as the Diuell would perſwad vs, thereby to cauſe vs to deſpaire.</p>
               <p>God in deed oftentimes ſendeth euilles
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2677:43"/> euen vpon his owne beloued children;<note place="margin">Why God ſendeth euils to his children, &amp; how he ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortes in the middeſt of euils.</note> but yet to the entent to do them good thereby: and withall in the middeſt of thoſe euils which he toucheth them with, he ſendeth them ſome comforts to holde their heartes with. Examples hereof you may ſee in <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Euah,</hi> for when for their diſobedience God would baniſh them out of that moſt pleaſant place in all the world, wherein at the firſt he had placed them, yet in the middeſt of that puniſhment which he had layde vppon them, his fatherly kindneſſe ſhewed it ſelfe; for before he droue them out, he made them coates to arme them againſt all weather,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.12.</note> and he comforted them with a promiſe of the <hi>bleſsed Seede (Ieſus Chriſt)</hi> which ſhould reſtore that ſaluation to mankind, which they had loſt by yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Serpents entyſings.</p>
               <p>This was, and this is, the moſt kind and louing dealing of God with man, he will make vs to ſmart a little for our ſinnes: heere is his iuſtice; but yet ſo, that he will not vtterly forſake vs, nor giue vs ouer for euer: heere is his mercie. Auoyde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Sathan,</hi> once I ſay againe auoyde: ceaſe to ſuggeſt or to ingeſt into any
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2677:44"/> mans hart, that he ſhould thinke becauſe that God doth croſſe &amp; afflict him, that therefore he doth hate, forſake, and vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſteth off thoſe with whom he ſo dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth: for this is moſt true, that as <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> hath taught vs to call vpon him by the name of a <hi>Father,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Our Father which art in heauen. &amp;c.</hi> ſo he loues vs as a Father for his ſake: and againe he will be more mindfull of vs, then our owne Mothers; for why? himſelfe hath ſo taught vs, and ſo promiſed, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in <hi>Eſa. 49.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 49.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Examine and conſider but a little the proceedinges and dealinges of Mothers and Fathers with their children,<note place="margin">How God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ealeth with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s children</note> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhall you ſee and perceiue more cleerely, how God handles his children vnder their afflictions, troubles, and croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p>It is the faſhion and manner of a good, kinde, and naturall Father, that faine would ſee good proofe of his child, firſt to inſtruct and teach him in the vertuous courſe and wayes of well doing: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to giue him o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tentimes warning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d monition, to keepe him in that good way which he hath taught him: Thirdly,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2677:44"/> if wordes will not ſerue, then to iercke him now and then with the rodde: Fourthly, in caſe his childe beeing now growen vp, waxe ſtubborne, malapart, and diſobedient, if he will needes ſpend his thrift wantonly, prodigally, and ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otouſly, in ill companie, then comes his Father and drawes him out by the eares, and with a whippe or cudgel, beates him till his boones cracke.</p>
               <p>All this he doth, and yet with a fatherly loue, and a naturall kind affection, to feare him, and to tame him; and as it were with violence, to bring him to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement, not minding to forſake him, nor vtterly to caſt him off for euer.</p>
               <p>Euen ſuch as this, is the dealing of our heauenly Father with his vntowardly, ſtubborne, and diſobedient children: For, firſt be teacheth and inſtructeth them by the Miniſters, Teachers, and Preachers of his holy word and will: he giueth them often monition and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to walke in his wayes, and to liue in his obedience; which if they deſpiſe and will not follow, then hee vſeth his rods, as pouertie, ſickneſſe, diſeaſes,<note place="margin">Gods rod of what ſo they are.</note> croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in their children, in their ſtocke, in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2677:45"/> their crop, and ſuch like: and when this will not ſerue, nor do any good, but ſtill on they waxe obſtinate and ſtubborne, and care not neither for wordes nor war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for ſtripes nor gentle correction; then God ſendeth vpon them more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie and greeuous puniſhments, as plages, peſtilences, dearth, caſualties of fire, wars, loſſe of victorie, fire and ſword, captiuitie, and other ſuch like great &amp; almoſt intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable miſchiefes: and all theſe to worke in them acknowleging of God, humbling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues vnder the mighty hand of God,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eketh to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orke by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dly with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> children</note> ſorrowfulnes of hart for their negligence in ſeruing of God, and true vnfayned re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and turning againe vnto God, who then is as ready to receiue them as euer he was before, and with mercie and louing kind benefites to bleſſe them: Examples hereof, holy Scriptures afforde vs not a few, but eſpecially in the gouene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> wherein it doth plainely appeare, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God did often times puniſh the diſobedience &amp; falling away of thoſe his people; yet it euer prooued nothing els, but the diſpleaſure of a kind and louing father, which ſought not their vtter ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2677:45"/> but rather their reformation and amendement. Let vs therefore in the like caſes, not deſpaire of Gods mercie, but amende our former wicked courſe of life, and yeeld our ſelues patiently vnto our heauenly father, and reioyce in him, in the middeſt of our troubles &amp; afflictions, for as much as there is nothing more ſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that if we returne to him, but he will like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe turne againe vnto vs with a gracious and fatherly minde, heart, and goodwill.</p>
               <p>In this behalfe alſo is God compared and likoned vnto a kind louing Mother;<note place="margin">Gods affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> children like vnto a kind louing Mothers ſection.</note> for like as a naturall Mother is very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, watchfull, &amp; diligent about her child, ſhe trimmeth it, ſhe dreſſeth it, feedeth it, nouriſheth it, prayeth to God hartely for it, and doth all the good ſhe can for it with a moſt louing, tender, &amp; motherly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and yet now and then ſhe is ſo diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted in her minde, ſo mooued and prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by her childs peltiſhnes, frowardnes, and vnrulines, that ſhe is euen againſt her owne nature, forced to be angrie with it, to chide it, &amp; ſometimes to beat it: Euen ſo like vnto this motherly dealing, is the propertie and naturall affection of God towardes mankind, who as he would not
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2677:46"/> the death of a ſinner, ſo neither delighteth he in any maner of griefe, ſorrow, trouble, or misfortune of man, were he not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſtirred vp, mooued, and prouoked, through our frowardnes, vnthankfulnes, and vnkindnes, to chaſten &amp; correct vs. And like as a Mother, though ſhe be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry &amp; offended with her child for a time, yet her diſpleaſure ſoone paſſeth away, ſhe giueth it not ouer, ſhe forſaketh it not, ſhe forgetteth it not for euer: Euen after the like faſhion doth God our heauenly Father deale with man. Nay more mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, more kind, and more pittifull is God towardes vs. This is moſt true, the mouth of God himſelfe hath ſpoken it; for theſe are his words.<note place="margin">9.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Can a Woman forget her owne Child, and not haue compaſſion on the ſonne of her wombe? though ſhe ſhould forget, yet will not I forget thee.</hi> And finally (to draw to an end of this compariſon) euen as a Mother when her child is impiſh, peeuiſh, and wayward, manaceth and threatneth it to throw it away to a Beggar, and ſcarreth it with ſome Bugges, Throſtes, Hobgob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, or ſuch like, &amp; all to make it quiet, and to cling the more vnto her: ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe our good Father, when he ſeeth that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2677:46"/> we forget him, make ſmaller reconing of him then becomes vs, and waxe vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vntowardly to all goodneſſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyning and haſting on apace to follow all ſinne and iniquitie; then he ſometimes ſheweth vs the terrible faces of fearefull troubles and dangers, and he will bring vs into great perilles: yea, and for our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe, and other ſuch like of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, he will now and then take away by one meanes or other, our health, our wealth, our peace, our libertie, our ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And all this doth hee to cauſe vs to turne backe againe vnto him, to cleaue and cling the faſter vnto him, to pray and call vpon him the more faythfully, hartely, and zelouſly for his helpe &amp; deliuerance, to eſteeme better of his giftes when we enioy them, and to be more thankefull for them when we haue them.</p>
               <p>So that the very cauſes of all our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, croſſes, and calamities, are not to worke in vs murmuring, &amp; grudging, and deſpaire; but if we wil waigh them &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them throughly, to make good vſe of them, they may turne to our great profite and benefite, and not to our hurt:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2677:47"/> For like as a naturall Father and Mother do, ſo doth God loue vs when he ſmiteth vs; he fauoureth vs, when he ſeemeth to be moſt againſt vs; when he ſeemeth to be moſt angry, he aymeth moſt at our good, for as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Meltus nouit medicus quid expediat quam aegrotus,</hi> The ſicke man the patient, neuer knoweth ſo well what is good for him as doth the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.<note place="margin">God dealeth with his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tions and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urgions do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith thier <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acientes.</note> And therefore the Phiſitions and Surgions when they ſee no other remedy for the recouerie, curing, and amending of their ſicke corrupted &amp; infected pacients, vſe to miniſter vnto them tart, bitter, harſh, and vnpleaſant things, and to ſeare, burne, &amp; cut away corrupted, rotten, and dead fleſh with ſawes, yron, and other ſuch like inſtruments, and all to ſaue and cheriſh the ſound and whole partes, <hi>Ne pars ſincera trahatur,</hi> leaſt that which is whole, ſhould by the other be corrupted, infected, &amp; poyſoned: Euen ſo doth God ſometimes (when he ſees it beſt for vs) plague our bodyes ſharpely &amp; greeuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that our ſoules may be preſerued and ſaued. The Phiſition in compounding of his beſt Triacle, vſeth Serpents, Adders, and other poyſoned things, that with the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2677:47"/> ſame he may driue out one poyſon with an other: Euen ſo God (as by Hiſtories plentifully in Gods Booke it appeares) vſeth the miniſterie, helpe,<note place="margin">How God vſeth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of Diuels and wicked men</note> and ſeruice of Diuels, and of moſt diuelliſh and wicked men, by them to afflict and chaſtice vs, and yet to do vs good withall; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes burneth the roddes when he hath corrected and beaten his children with them awhile. It is not giuen to euery man (I muſt needes confeſſe) to vnderſtande this, &amp; to make this good vſe of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, croſſes, &amp; troubles layde vpon them for their ſins ſake;<note place="margin">The wicked are not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions,</note> for then ſhould <hi>Pharao</hi> and many of his wicked courtyers, like himſelfe then ſhould <hi>Cain, Saul, Iudas Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariot,</hi> and many other vile leawde and deſperat perſons beſide, in their manifold croſſes, troubles, and aduerſities, haue turned vnto the Lord and been ſaued. But we muſt learne &amp; know, that aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, troubles, and afflictions, of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and of their owne proper nature,<note place="margin">Whence it commeth that afflicti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and croſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s profit Gods children.</note> can not worke &amp; bring ſuch profites, and ſo much good vnto men: But it is the ſpirit of God, which reſting in Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full children, purgeth, reformeth, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, &amp; ſtrengtheneth them, and by theſe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2677:48"/> outward meanes worketh all theſe good thinges in vs: And ſo whatſoeuer good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath been ſpoken of heretofore to befal men by meanes of aduerſities, croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp; troubles, is to be vnderſtanded only of the faythfull and godly, which are taught and ledde by the ſpirit of God, to conſider rightly of them, and to make ſuch vſe of them, that according as in the beginning of this Chapter it is truely ſayd, to them <hi>that loue God, all thinges worke together for the beſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas on the otherſide, in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faythfull, vnrepentant, and wicked ones, they worke after an other faſhion, and are of cleane contrary operation,<note place="margin">The conceits &amp; opinions of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in their aduerſities &amp; troubles.</note> whiles that they aſcribe their aduerſities and troubles, either to blinde Fortune and Chaunce; as though Fortune had a certaine power to worke, without the working and prouidence of God; or els, vnto them that are not of their owne ſect, fayth, and religion, as did wicked <hi>Ahab</hi> to godly <hi>Elias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4. King. 18.</note> or to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, or to the Miniſters of Gods word, or to Fayth and Religion it ſelfe, or to the Planets, Starres, and influences of the Elements; yea, and ſome will blame God
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2677:48"/> him ſelfe, as though they them ſelues were ſo innocent and blameleſſe, that God deales not well with them to lay vppon them ſuch croſſes and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes: and ſo very buſie they make themſelues, to ſhift off all blame euer to otheres faultes.</p>
               <p>And although their ſinnes be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to exceeding multitudes of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, yet they will not ſee nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe any ſuch thinges in them ſelues, nor any thing conſider, nor regarde the puniſhmentes of God layde vppon them, and cleauing vnto them for the ſame. But through their hardneſſe of hart, and want of fayth (which is the mother of all blaſphemie &amp; abhomination) they can not ſpy whoſe hand it is that is againſt them, nor wherefore; or els beeing euen as it were violently forced to know it, that it is the working of the Lord againſt them, and his vengeance in heauie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure vpon them; yet they will not be mooued thereby, nor any thing at all ſtirred vp to amende their lyues but like vnto King <hi>Pharao,</hi> the more God cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth them, the more obſtinatly they ſwarue, decline, and flie away from him,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2677:49"/> being like vnto graceleſſe children, with whom neither wordes, threatninges, nor beating, can preuaile. Like vnto them that will neither daunce with the piper,<note place="margin">Math. 11.17. Luk. 7.31 32</note> nor lament with the mourner: And ſo farre off are they from being recouered, won, and reformed by meanes of any croſſes, afflictions &amp; troubles lighting on them; and following them euen as the ſhadow doth the body; that they will ſooner burſt out into all maner of impatientnes, bitternes, and ſpightfull poyſonfull ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and blaſpheming wordes againſt the righteouſnes of God, ſaying, That their puniſhment is greater then their ſinnes, and heauier then they can brooke or beare: and that they are wronged, and are not indifferently dealt with, and ſo at the length after heaping one ſinne in the necke of an other, the Diuell brings them on, and by little and little windes them into that he gapes for,<note place="margin">The endes that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel bringes the wicked vnto by their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, troubles and croſſes.</note> namely into a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate minde, and deadly Deſperation, in ſo much that at the laſt they fall to, and yeelde to murthering, hanging, drowning, or by other ſuch meanes moſt miſerably, to diſpatch themſelues with their owne handes, like vnto <hi>Saule, Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel,</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:2677:49"/> &amp; <hi>Iudas,</hi> ſo giuing them ſelues ouer to the Diuell; and as they lyued for a while moſt wretchedly, ſo they depart out of the world as diuelliſhly, forgetting vtterly, &amp; altogether inconſiderate, retch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and careleſſe what ſhall become of them afterwards for euer. By whoſe liues,<note place="margin">Two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities to be reaped by the liues and maner of the death of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</note> and maner of deathes the children of God may yet reape two commodities: firſt, they ſhall be eaſed of the great troubles, diſturbance, and diſcommoditis, and of the leawd and euill examples which they gaue to others whiles they lyued. And ſecondly, they which remaine aliue after them, may learne and take warning by their ſhamefull fals, and by their terrible examples, and deſperate deaths, lay hold on repentance and amendement of their lyues before it be too late.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Sixt Chapter concerning the Remedies againſt Deſperation, ariſing and growing by long cuſtome of ſinne, and by delaying &amp; put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the forſaking of ſinne from day to day.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT is written, that the continuall and long cuſtome of ſinne, and the delaying,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2677:50"/> and putting off from time to time of the amendement of life,<note place="margin">The great danger of cuſtome of ſinne, and of delaying of amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life.</note> is one of the greateſt and moſt dangerous deceites, and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſtratagems and pollicies which the enemie of mankind doth vſe towards the children of <hi>Adam:</hi> for he is not ignorant how that like as Linkes in a Chaine one catcheth hold and hangeth by an other, and one draweth an other: Euen ſo by continuance, long cuſtome, and ſecure ſleeping in ſinne, one ſinne draweth on an other, and ſo euery day ſinne is added to ſinne, ſo that by tolleration and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſtination, ſinne ſo mightely encreaſeth, &amp; by this meanes waxeth ſo headſtrong, that in the end, the ſaying of the Poet prooueth very true; to wit,
<q>Qui non eſt hodie, oras minus aptus erit.</q> Hee that is not ready to day (to forgoe &amp; forſake ſinne) to morrow-day ſhall he be more vnfit.<note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhewing the danger of long cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome and weltering in ſinnes.</note> The Diuell knoweth well enough, how that like as old feſtered and long growe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoares &amp; diſeaſes of the body, are farre more dangerous, more trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and harder to be healed, &amp; require a longer time by much to be cured, then if they had bin looked to at the firſt: Euen ſo the diſeaſes of the ſoule, as ſwearing,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2677:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> theeuing whoring, drunkennes, and ſuch like, being once long accuſtomed, ſetled, &amp; hauing gotten an habite, are either ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, or ſeldome, and that with greater dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie afterwardes rooted out, then at the firſt beginning they might haue been.</p>
               <p>And ſo by theſe diſeaſes of the ſoule, the habite thereof hauing once taken roote in man and the Diuell by them hauing got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the ſurer hold and poſſeſsion, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reth &amp; moſt diligently by all wayes and meanes applyeth to keepe men ſtill on in vre, and practiſe with old and long accuſtomed ſinnes, vntill at the length in extremitie of ſickneſſe towards the how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of death (if not before) hee may by ſuch cauſes and occaſions plant &amp; worke in the heart of man deepe deſpaire, to his vtter confuſion for euer.</p>
               <p>To reſiſt therefore, to remedie and helpe this cankerlike creeping &amp; infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous euill, let vs to day while it is yet to day, ſtudy to turne againe vnto God, caſt out the Diuel, and with him this great cauſe and occaſion of Deſperation, euen long cuſtome of ſinne, and delay of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement of our liues, the thing that ſo
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2677:51"/> hangeth on, and preſſeth vs downe, &amp; let vs in time while we haue time, take a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter courſe, looking vp vnto <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and ſet him before the eyes of our fayth, as the only marke to ſhoot at. And for as much as we can not turne againe vnto the Lord, &amp; forſake our former wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our former long accuſtomed ſins, except the Lord our God reach vs his helping hand to turne vs vnto him; and that repentance is not in our owne power to take it vp,<note place="margin">Whence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entance &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> life are to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> had, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me by.</note> &amp; lay it downe at our owne pleaſure, and that of our ſelues we can not put it into, nor plant it in our heartes when and where we liſt, except it firſt come from aboue; for that it is an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and a rare gift of God: Let vs ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and hartely with our humble and feruent prayers begge and craue the ſame at Gods hands: Let vs practiſe much and often hearing, reading &amp; meditating the word of God, and with care &amp; diligence vſe all ordinary meanes for the better, more ready, and ſpeedie attaining of it: for it is not ſo eaſie a matter to be come by, as the world thinketh it: It is not an howers worke when we lie on our death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beds, that will ſerue the turne: It is not,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2677:51"/> Cry God mercy a little for faſhion ſakes that will do it:<note place="margin">Many are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> may be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiued in the maner time of their repe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance.</note> It is not a courſing or mumbling vp of a few Prayers at a mans laſt farewell, that will auayle: And yet if we were ſure that that would ſerue, yet we are very vnſure, whether we ſhal haue time and leaſure, wit, ſenſes, reaſon, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce at our laſt gaſpe to do that yea or no. To truſt to do it at our laſt hower, is but a broken ſtaffe to be relyed on and truſted vnto: And yet it is not ſo vncertaine, but on the other ſide it is as certaine, that then we ſhall haue many byaſſes and barres, many rubbes &amp; ſtops,<note place="margin">Note th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> your laſt end.</note> many lets and impedimentes to lie in our wayes, and to hinder our courſe in going forward at that time with laſt gaſping repentaunce, which many infatuated, fond, &amp; fooliſh men relie ſo much vpon, and truſt ſo much vnto, paſsing away their dayes, and careleſly neglecting good opportunitie when time ſerueth, like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe fiue fooliſh Virgins that made no preparation aforehand to be in a readines to enter in with the Bride-groome, till it was too late: this is I ſay, a very broken ſtaffe to truſt vnto, &amp; a thing very doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vncertaine to depende vpon, or
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2677:52"/> to make any reckoning of, for a man to repent and cry God mercie, and make himſelfe fit and ready for God at his laſt hower, becauſe that very many in al ages, and in all places haue been, and are taken away oftentimes with a ſodaine death, and haue neither that howers nor halfe howers leaſure that they before ſpake ſo much of, and truſted ſo much vnto.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uke 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amples <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ewing that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hower. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n 19.23.</note>When the World was <hi>eattng and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, planting and buylding:</hi> when they were moſt ſecure and careleſſe, then ſodainely came the Flood, and ouerwhelmed them all. Though it were a faire morning at <hi>Lots</hi> going out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> yet by and by when they leaſt thought of any ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they were all ſodainely deſtroyed. When <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was moſt brag,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni. 4.12.</note> and thought himſelfe moſt ſafe and ſure, ſodainely (neuer dreaming nor once ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting any ſuch thinges) was he pulled on his knees.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke. 12.20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es. 5. are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o notable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mples of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aine and prouided <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nias &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wife.</note> The Rich man thought himſelfe neuer more like to haue lyued, then when he ſo buſily made ſuch great prouiſion, and layde vp ſtoore for many yeares: yet was his ſoule ſodainely taken from him the very ſame night. And what knoweſt thou ô man! that truſteſt ſo
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2677:52"/> much, and putteſt off till the laſt day and hower, whether that day and hower may not come as ſodainely on thee, and as vnlooked for, as it did on any of theſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe</hi> did write one of them to the other, what his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion was concerning the ſtate of an olde Adulterer which in their time, as he was going in the night time to his Whoore, paſsing ouer a Bridge in his way, fell into the Riuer; and ſo being drowned, was taken away ſodainely in the very pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of his wickedneſſe, hauing ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hower, halfe hower, nor minute, to crie God mercie, to repent and to pray in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ioannes Riuius,</hi> a learned Writer,<note place="margin">Lib. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtultia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mortali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in procr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nanda rection vitae.</note> and of good credite, affirmed that in his time, and in a Village of his country, two olde men lying with their Whores whom they had aforetime haunted, in one and the ſelfeſame night dyed, ſodainely taken as it were with the maner; hauing likewiſe neither hower nor halfe hower to prepare themſelues in: for the one was ſodainely ſtabbed to death; the other was taken with a ſodaine Apoplexie, whereof he preſently gaue vp his Ghoſt.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:2677:53"/>
               <p>And what knoweth any of vs all, or what greater priuildge hath any of vs all, but that we may be ſodainly preuented, &amp; caried away in the mideſt of our ſinnes as theſe were? And whether we haue not the like examples of ſuch haſtie deathes heere in England, whereby many of vs haue been diſappoynted of theſe two or three howers at their laſt end, to make vs readie in, I report me to the deathes of <hi>Earle Godwin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>efull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h.</note> and <hi>Grimwood</hi> of <hi>Hitcham?</hi> whereof the Earle after he had trayterouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſlaine the brother of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, being charged afterwardes by the King therwith at <hi>Windſore</hi> (where he hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to ſit at table with the King) hee falſely denyed the fact, and for his better excuſe, hee falſely forſware it; and beſides all this, he moreouer tooke a peece of bread and put it into his mouth, wiſhed that he might be choaked thereof, if hee were guiltie of his blood; and it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in deed according to this deſire: for hee beeing choaked therewith, yeeled vp his Ghoſt, and fell downe dead in the preſence and ſight of all at the Table, and from thence was had to <hi>Wincheſter</hi> to be buried. And likewiſe the ſayd <hi>Grimwood</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:2677:53"/> of <hi>Hitcham</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Suffolke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Grimwood his ſodaine and feareful death.</note> knowen to be a wilfull forſworne man, in the Harueſt time next after his periurie, feeling no paine, complayning of no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, being ſtrong and able to labour, as he was ſtacking vp Corne, ſodainely his Bowels fell out of his body, whereof im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly he dyed moſt miſerably.</p>
               <p>But what need I to ſtand beſtowing time, paper, and incke, troubling both my ſelfe &amp; future Readers, in ſetting downe the maner of the ſodaine deaths of many men, ſeeing that both holy and prophane Writers, &amp; dayly experience it ſelfe, may fully fraught, ſtore, and furniſh vs with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite examples of this ſort? And what charter, priuiledge, or certaine holde of life hath any of vs all, more then theſe heere before recited, or thouſandes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the like caſe haue had?</p>
               <p>O let vs not preſume therfore to runne on headlong in the long and hardened cuſtome of our ſinnes! nor to delay and put off the reforming of our wicked liues vntil the laſt hower: And although we be not ſtriken with ſodaine death, but haue both certaine dayes and howers before our death, yet (as I before ſayd) full many
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2677:54"/> are the ſtoppes; lets, and impedimentes, which both may, &amp; alſo dayly do fall out to hinder &amp; put by this late repentance, that ſo many will needes truſt vnto,<note place="margin">A catalogue of lets and impedimnts which often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fall out when we come to the laſt hower, that hinder and put by that late re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, which ſo many truſt vnto.</note> and make all their reckoning of, putting off from day to day, &amp; from yeare to yeare, till this laſt time approch and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l on them in deed: For ſo long as the extremities of ſicknes do nippe and pinch our mortall bodyes, the doloure, panges, and paynes racking and tormenting our fleſh, will keepe our mindes ſo occupied, ſometime calling on the Phiſition for helpe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time turning, toſsing, and ſeeking for eaſe in euery corner of the bed; yea, and from bed to bed, while ſtrength doth ſerue: ſometime taking this Receipt, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that, as the Phiſitions ſhall mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: ſometimes turmoyled and occupied both in minde and body by the working and purging of the Apothecarie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> drugges receiued, ſometimes diſquiet and braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with thoſe that are attending about vs, crying out on them, as though their vſing and handling of vs were the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our greater panges and paines: with theſe and ſuch like circumſtaunces, are both bodyes and mindes exerciſed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2677:54"/> and vexed, ſo long as the vigour and ſtrength of fleſh and blood are able to endure and hold out, and ſo buſied here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with continually, that we ſeldome haue any reſt or leaſure to frame our ſelues to any quiet calling on God; to any repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, or vnfaigned and zelous crying for mercie: for if we ſometimes endeuour our ſelues to begin to go about it, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold one thing or other ſoone ſtriketh all out of minde, and diſturbes vs ſo, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a whit the better: But if after the powers and ſenſes of our bodyes be once worne and weakened, and the feeling of the extreame dolours and pangues of the ſickneſſe be mittigated, wherby the body after a time of wreſtling and wearying of it ſelfe is now ſomewhat quieted,<note place="margin">Moe lets <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of late re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> conuerting to God.</note> and ſo the minde more ſetled, we then begin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to take better holde, yet ſtill on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the care of children &amp; wife, for want of ſufficient prouiſion for them, or griefe to depart from them, or the remembrance of landes, goodes, houſes, and poſſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and other worldly treaſures; the loue, liking, and delights whereof haue poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our heartes all our life time before, will now ſo afreſh enter and trouble our
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2677:55"/> heades and mindes; that yet time ſerues not for to continue any ſuch godly and chriſtian exerciſes as we in health time when we ſhould haue done it, made no account of, and deferred vntill the laſt hower.<note place="margin">The effectes of choler, in time of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame ſicknes.</note> Sometimes are we troubled and diſeaſed with melancholy and frenſies, choler ſhooting vp into our braines, and with ſuch crampes &amp; convultions cauſed by much euacuation, and ſuch abundance of choler in our vaines, that hereof fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes the natural effectes, rauinges, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemings, vnſenſible talking, wrything of the lippes, ſtrange and vnaccuſtomed wreſting and turning of the necke, buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the ioyntes &amp; whole body; yea &amp; often times ſuch extraordinay ſtrength, that three or foure men can not hold vs nor rule vs without bondes. With theſe and ſuch like ſtrange effectes, are many men depriued not onely of the right vſe of the partes of their bodyes, but alſo of their reaſon &amp; right wittes, and laſt of all of life it ſelfe. Are not heere then lettes and ſtayes enough from the performance of that amendement of life, prayer, and crying God mercy, which we proroged and put off in our life time?</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:2677:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Put caſe that we be neither cut off with ſodaine death, nor annoyed at our laſt end with any of theſe aforeſayd lets and impediments of ſtrange diſeaſes and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary effectes thereof, nor with any other ſuch like noyſome &amp; troubleſome circumſtaunces or ſickneſſes, but that we haue time, leaſure, and quietneſſe to do all ſuch things as any of vs al truſted vnto at our laſt farewell with the world?<note place="margin">The Diuel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> will be mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> buſie to hin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance at o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> laſt hower.</note> yet will that deadly enemie, that mortall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſay of ours <hi>Sathan</hi> the Diuell, at that time aboue all other apply himſelfe; and let vs looke for no other, but what vile ſinne we haue committed &amp; delighted in in all our life time, that will he lay to our charge, and clogge our conſcienſes with, &amp; to bring vs into deſperation with and by them, he will put vs in minde, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie vs with Gods ſeuere threatninges againſt ſinne. Hee will obiect againſt vs that ſaying of our Lord Chriſt,<note place="margin">Matth. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>that if we would haue entred into life, we ſhould haue kept his Commaundements.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> Hee will tell vs that not hee that <hi>ſayth Lord, Lord, but hee that doth the will of the father of he uen, ſhall enter into the kingdome of God.</hi> Hee will put vs in minde that, <hi>Not the hearers of the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2677:56"/> Law,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2. Rom. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>but the doers ſhall be iuſtified.</hi> Hee will threaten vs, that <hi>becauſe we haue liued ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh, we ſhall die.</hi> Hee will cracke vs,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor. 6.9.10.</note> that <hi>the vnrighteous ſhall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite the kingdome of God: and that neither Fornicators, nor Idolaters, nor Adulterers, nor Wantons, nor Buggerers, nor Theeues, nor the Couetous, nor Drunkards, nor Raylors, nor Extortioners, ſhall inherite the kingdome of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that ſuch as haue lyued accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the workes of the fleſh, which are repeated vp <hi>Gala 5.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> ſhall not attaine to the kingdome of God.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er. 2.</note> And that wee muſt be preſented before the iudgement ſeate of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Apocal. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>and euery man receiue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly according as he hath done in this life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Peter. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>good or euill: euery man ſhall receiue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his workes. And that God ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not the Angels when they ſinned.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>And if the Iuſt ſhall ſcarce be ſaued, where ſhall the Wicked man and ſinner appeare?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When all theſe, and a great deale more, deſcribing and ſetting foorth vnto vs the rigour of Gods ſeueare iuſtice, and the reckoning wherevnto wee ſhall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſhall be put into our mindes on our
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2677:56"/> death-beds; and that damned <hi>Sathan,</hi> which all the dayes of our liues before, laboured to make vs careleſſe and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of the knowledge, or conſideration of any of theſe thinges, that ſo he might make vs the more boldly and blindly to runne headlong into ſinne, ſhall charge vs with this, and much more like ſtuffe, appealling to our owne conſciences for witneſſe hereof, and ſo herevpon plant in our guiltie heartes deepe Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Alas in what caſe ſhall our poore ſoules then ſtand? Would a man then for a thouſand worldes, and all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites and pleaſures thereof, be brought to ſuch a quandarie?</p>
               <p>O thou therefore that readeſt or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt this damnable and miſerable ſtate that ſillie ſoules may be implunged into, for the better auoyding of theſe perilles, reade, &amp; reade againe, meditate, ponder, and put in practiſe the direction, aduice, and counſayle in the beginning of this preſent ſixt Chapter.<note place="margin">The exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph of Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathia, moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be imitated.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And take this leſſon of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia,</hi> that like as he in his life time had made readie a Sepulcre in the middeſt
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2677:57"/> of his Garden, which was the place of his pleaſure (as all Gardens of great men moſt commonly are:) Euen ſo thou in the middeſt of theſe things wherein thou takeſt thy greateſt felicitie and delight, remember yet thy Graue, and what one day (thou knoweſt not how ſoone) ſhall become of thy poore ſoule, and afterward of thy ſoule and body for euer.</p>
               <p>Remember and learne likewiſe at the <hi>Egiptians,</hi> who perceiuing the mindful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of death to be a good helpe to bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle their euill actions,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he vſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtome of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Egipti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns.</note> vſed to bring a Picture or Image reſembling Death, into their great and ſolemne Feaſtes; which fearefull and ouglie ſight, trembling and ſhaking they tooke to be a ſpeciall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to keepe the beholders in ſobrietie, by the remembrance of their end, which they muſt all come vnto ſooner or later.</p>
               <p>And finally, learne at the good King <hi>Ezechias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he notable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd imitable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xample of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hias.</note> when thou ſhalt be by any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion put in the remembraunce of death, be af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aide of Gods threatninges, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a little before hand, leaſt thou be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to ſorrow, howle, and cry reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ddeſſe alwayes afterwardes: for accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the old ſaying, <hi>Qui ante non ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uebit
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2677:57"/> poſt dolebit,</hi> he that will not beware before, ſhall afterward be ſory.<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus. 7.40.</note> And hee that in all his doinges remembreth the end, ſhall neuer lightly do amiſſe: The which wiſe remembraunce of our endes, he vouchſafe to plant in our hearts, who hath full dearely bought vs, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> the righteous; to whom with his, and our heauenly Father, and the holy Spirit, three perſons; and one eternall maieſtie of Godhead, all worthy glorie, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and prayſe, be worthely attributed for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:2677:58"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The ſeuenth Chapter conteyning the Generall Preſeruatiue againſt the deſpaire or doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods mercie aryſing vpon any cauſe whatſoeuer.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>FOr as much as it is a thing manifeſtly to be prooued by holy Scriptures, that a man endued with true fayth it ſelfe, may notwithſtanding now and then be toubled and aſſaulted with motions of doubtinges, wauering; yea and of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing: therefore for the brideling, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing, and ouercomming of theſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes, it ſhall be good to put in practiſe theſe fiue thinges eſpecially.</p>
               <p>Firſt, we are to thinke and conſider thus much,<note place="margin">The firſt preſeruatiue againſt Deſpaire.</note> that as not to murther, not to ſteale, not to commit adulterie, and all the reſt of the Decalogue or ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, are the Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of God, and we are carefull, and ſtriue with our ſelues that wee ſhould not breake any of them; leaſt that in brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any of them, we ſhould ſo highly offend God, that he would therefore powre downe vpon vs his heauie wrath,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2677:58"/> and in his indignation ſeueerely puniſh vs, as by many examples wee ſee he hath done to others in the like offences: So alſo it is Gods commaundement as well as any of the other are,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.23.</note> 
                  <hi>That wee beleeue in the name of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> and therefore we muſt thinke wee offende againſt God as greeuouſly, or rather farre more greeuouſly in violating and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this Commaundement by incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, doubting, wauering, and deſpairing, as if we ſhould ſhed mans blood, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit whoredome, theft, periurie, or any other ſuch like notorious ſinne.</p>
               <p>O what a haynous ſinne muſt it needes be to caſt no doubtes, nor deſpaire in the helpe of a mortall man in the time of neede! and yet to miſtruſt and deſpaire of the like in God? As for example: We can ſettle our heartes to beleeue in our mortall Fathers if we ſtand in neede of meate, drinke, or cloathes,<note place="margin">An exam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> that man men put more tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in morta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> man ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God.</note> wee then call on them: and if they promiſe vs any ſuch thinges, we can ſet our heartes at caſe, and count it as a thing done; we doubt nothing of their good wil towards vs, nor of the performaunce of their word vnto vs, wee depende vppon them, wee relye
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:2677:59"/> onely on them and none other, and what they giue their word to do for vs, we make as ſure reckoning of it, as if it were alreadie in our handes.</p>
               <p>Againe, if we ſtand in neede of a peece of money as of x.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xample <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ewing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ore truſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> mortall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> God.</note> xx. li. xxx. li. or be it more or leſſe, to diſcharge ſome dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Bond, or for any ſuch like vſe by a ſet day, or to ſaue our bodyes out of priſon; and in the meane time, before the day appointed come, ſome one of our honeſt rich neighbours, that is counted an honeſt ſubſtantial man, and of good credite, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe vs certainly ſo much money as we want, and ſtand in need of to ſerue our turne with, and bids vs truſt vnto it, that before that day he will be ſure to helpe; we herevpon truſt his honeſt promiſe, we beleeue his word, &amp; make as ſure ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it as if we had it already in our purſes, and take no more thought nor care for it. O how much more ſhould we truſt Gods moſt faythfull, iuſt, and true word and promiſe; beleeue him without all diſtruſt, doubting, or deſpaire, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende vpon him who is a thouſand times more able and more willing to do vs good, and to keepe touch with vs, then
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:2677:59"/> euer was, or euer ſhalbe any mortall earthly Father, or friendly neigbour?</p>
               <p>The ſecond thing in this caſe to be conſidered of is, that euery one of vs,<note place="margin">The ſecond generall help againſt deſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ation.</note> is particularly to beleeue that he is in the number of thoſe that ſhalbe ſaued, by the merites of Chriſtes death &amp; paſſion: for the promiſes of ſaluation in Chriſt are indefinite, excluding no particuler man, as for example: <hi>God ſo loued the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 3 16.</note> 
                  <hi>that he gaue his onely beloued Sonne, to the end that all that beleeue in him ſhould not periſh, but haue life euerlaſting.</hi> In which generall wordes, is included euery particuler be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing perſon, although he haue not his name ſeuerally &amp; particulerly ſet downe: and heere God excludeth none from his promiſe, vnleſſe through their vnbeleefe and deſpaire, they exclude their owne ſelues. If the King of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> of his owne meere mercie, and motion of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion, or at the ſure and mediation of ſome Noble man or other that is deare vnto him, ſhould freely pardon and forgiue all the malefactors and priſoners of any Gaile, within his Kingdomes, may we not account them very fond &amp; fooliſh men, and not worthy the benefite of the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2677:60"/> Kinges gracious Pardon, if ſome two or three ſhould doubt and deſpaire that this generall Pardon appertained not vnto them, becauſe their owne perticular and ſeuerall names were not therein ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and expreſſed? Euen thus is our caſe.</p>
               <p>Let not therefore any illuſion of <hi>Sathan,</hi> nor feare of our owne vnworthineſſe, nor want of our perticular names, nor any other argument or reaſon whatſoeuer, withdraw vs from challenging our owne portions and partes of Gods moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull promiſes, of his free pardone, and remiſsion of our ſinnes: Let vs not doubt nor diſtruſt the performaunce and trueth of Gods promiſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e third <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nerall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pe againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſperation.</note>Thirdly, to comfort our ſelues, and to ſuppreſſe <hi>Sathans</hi> temptations to deſpay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, we may further meditate and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with our ſelues theſe two poyntes eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially: Firſt, that ſeeing the Lord hath promiſed to forgiue our ſinnes, &amp; to put all our wickedneſſe out of his remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance (as by plaine and moſt manifeſt euidence of holy Scriptures it may eaſily be prooued) then it ſtandeth with his iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice and trueth, to performe the ſame, and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2677:60"/> that vpon ſuch a neceſsitie, that he muſt either forgiue vs our offences according to his owne word, or els we muſt count him vnfaythfull for the breach of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; or els (which were horrible to thinke) iudge him an hipocrite or a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembler, if he ſhould pretend one thing, and intend another; or at the leaſt wiſe vnconſtant in altering and changing that which he hath ſpoken with his owne mouth, &amp; ſo to be thought (which is mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous) to be vniuſt: For the ſecond poynt, we may conſider likewiſe to our comfort, and to the weakning &amp; ouerthrow of all deſperate conceites,<note place="margin">Eſai. 75.</note> that <hi>God hath alreadie puniſhed Ieſus Chriſt for our offences,</hi> &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can not in iuſtice puniſh them againe in vs. We offended, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> was puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for the ſame.<note place="margin">what ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> could b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> looked at ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> handes what ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> man co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> be cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diſcha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> What ſoeuer in iuſtice God could either demaund, or man owed, that paide our Lord <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Man ought to die, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſatisfied for the ſame: Man ought to haue borne the heauie wrath &amp; diſpeaſure of <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  </hi> father, <hi>Chriſt</hi> did beare the ſame: Man ought to haue bin caſt downe into hell, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſatisfied for that alſo: yea, he ſo fully contented, payed, &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God the Father, for all whatſoeuer
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2677:61"/> the Lord could looke for at mans hands, that the Father himſelfe acknowledged, and in thunder from heauen confeſſed the ſame, in the hearing of many witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes preſent; and hearing the ſame at the baptizing of our Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> by <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt in the Flood <hi>Iorden:</hi> And ſo all faythfull beleeuers hereof, are hereby fully and freely acquitte and diſcharged from all debt of ſinne they owed vnto God, for euer.</p>
               <p>Why ſhould thou then, ô <hi>Sathan!</hi> ſo buſily charge vs with any ſuch matter, to driue vs into deſperation, ſeeing that <hi>Sublata cauſa tollitur etiam &amp; effectus?</hi> The cauſe whereby thou ſo vrgeſt deſperation by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> being taken away, the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes alſo muſt needes then ceaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e fourth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pherall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pe for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ring.</note>The fourth thing to be vſed and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed for the better auoyding of Deſpaire, is that at what time ſoeuer wee feele our heartes through <hi>Sathans</hi> craftie ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aſſaulted and moleſted with this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous ſting of Deſperation, we ſhould then ſtraight way conuey our ſelues into ſome quiet and ſecret place, and there in ſome humble maner powre out our harts before God with inward harty, &amp; zelous
<pb facs="tcp:2677:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> prayer, deſiring him of his infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to worke in our heartes increaſe of fayth, and to ſuppreſſe and vanquiſh all our vnbeleefe, and vtterly to expell from thence all deſpaire.</p>
               <p>The fift and laſt Remedie that now I purpoſe to handle heere againſt Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> againſt o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peration.</note> is that we frame our ſelues care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, diligintly, and with godly zeale to vſe, and ofentimes to frequent ſuch godly meanes as God hath appoynted and ſet foorth vnto vs, for the obtayning and increaſing of fayth, as (ouer and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides earneſt praier, laſt before ſpoken of) the vſe of reuerent reading, hearing, and meditating of Gods word, and the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Sacramentes, being holy Signes, and as it were Scales ſeene with our outward or bodily eyes, which inwardly do ſignifie, and ſet foorth to our heartes the ſecret and inward graces of God.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
